<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Christ-Church in Dublin before the Lord Lieutenant and Council, the fifth day of July, 1674 by Mr. Andrew Sall ...</title>
            <author>Sall, Andrew, 1612-1682.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 163 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 81 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60320</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S392</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32075</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12319005</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12319005</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59434</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60320)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59434)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1026:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Christ-Church in Dublin before the Lord Lieutenant and Council, the fifth day of July, 1674 by Mr. Andrew Sall ...</title>
                  <author>Sall, Andrew, 1612-1682.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[39], 120 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Benjamin Tooke ... and are to be sold by Joseph Wilde ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dvblin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Apologetic works.</term>
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59434:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59434:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at CHRIST-CHURCH IN DUBLIN, Before the <hi>Lord Lieutenant</hi> and <hi>Council,</hi> The Fifth day of <hi>July,</hi> 1674.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>Mr.</hi> ANDREW SALL, Formerly of the <hi>Order of Ieſus,</hi> and Profeſſor of Divinity in the Colledges of <hi>Pamplona, Polencia,</hi> and <hi>Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dela</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> Rector and Profeſſor of Controverſies in the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Colledge of the Univerſity of <hi>Salamanca,</hi> Profeſſor of <hi>Moral Theology</hi> in the Royal Colledge of the Society in the ſame Univerſity, now Preacher of the Goſpel in the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Church of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and Chaplain to his Excellency the moſt Honourable <hi>ARTH<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>R</hi> Earl of <hi>Eſſex,</hi> Lord Lieutenant General, and General Governour of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Not unto us, O Lord, not unto us, but unto thy Name give glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, for thy mercy and for thy truths ſake,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalm. 115.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>I will ſpeak of thy teſtimonies, alſo before Kings, and will not be aſhamed,</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſalm 119.46.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Authority.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN,</hi> Printed by <hi>Benjamin Tooke,</hi> Printer to his King's moſt Excellent Majeſty; and are to be ſold by <hi>Joſeph Wilde</hi> Book-ſeller in <hi>Caſtle-ſtreet,</hi> 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:59434:2"/>
            <p>Imprimatur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>JA: ARMACANUS</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:59434:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:59434:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59434:3"/>
            <head>To His Excelleney, THE MOST HONOURABLE, ARTHUR Earl of ESSEX, Viſcount <hi>Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den,</hi> Baron <hi>Capel</hi> of <hi>Hadham,</hi> Lord Lieutenant General, and General Governour of His Majeſties King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Ireland,</hi> Lord Lieutenant of the County of <hi>Hertford,</hi> and one of the Lords of His Majeſties moſt Honourable Privy Council.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Excellency,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE love of Truth made me forſake what I loved moſt of worldly things, and occaſioned my dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt friends to become my bitter
<pb facs="tcp:59434:4"/>Enemies<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Tyranny did ſtop my mouth formerly from ſpeaking Truth, and malice ſubrogated now doth purſue me even where I expected liberty, being buſy, as I am informed, in contriving (if not my deſtruction) my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>credit, that I might not be able to ſpeak againſt errours, too much prevailing in the world, or not to be credited, when I ſhould do it.</p>
            <p>The ſame of your Excellency's Heroick Endowments, &amp; Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Zeal of Truth and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, derived from your illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Progenitors, and more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately from your moſt hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ourable and renowned Father of glorious memory, for ſacrifice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his life to Truth and Loyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb facs="tcp:59434:4"/>did encourage me to addreſs my ſelf to your Excellency's Protection in this more than or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary neceſſity thereof. The moſt gracious reception your Excellency was pleaſed to give me, emboldened me to manifeſt the juſtification of my departure from the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Communion, and adhereing to the purity of Catholick Religion, as it is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> in a Sermon Preached at the Royal Chappel of <hi>Chriſt-Church,</hi> in your Honourable Preſence. And the ſingular <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnity wherewith your Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy &amp; your Iluſtrious <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> was pleaſed to hear, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> prove of my diſcourſe upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Subject, giveth me confiden<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:59434:5"/>to preſent to your Excellency, &amp; commend to your protection the ſame Diſcourſe being ordered to publiſh it, That being Hon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oured in the Front with your Excellency's Illuſtrious Name, it might the better withſtand the aſſaults of envy and malice.</p>
            <p>The adverſaries of our Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine are ſo active in advancing their Faction, that where they cannot practice Violence, their contrivances do reach to terrify Sincere mindes from profeſſing or ſpeaking what they judgright. I have but too much ground to think it is ſo with very many in this Country and abroad, It is more want of courage, than of knowledge, that keeps many good men under their yoke, and ſuch as know their ways,
<pb facs="tcp:59434:5"/>may think it a wonder that any who were among them of note, ſhould dare to oppoſe them. It will be a ſingular glory of your Excellency, if under your ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter we may enjoy the freedom of ſpeaking Truth. Peace is the Foundation of Happineſs and Luſtre in any Government, and the fierceſt Enemy of Peace is Diſſenſion in Religion. Of ſuch Diſſenſion, the only remedy by ordinary Providence, is, a free exchange of reaſons, according to the Rule of God's Word, and within the Bounds of Chriſtian Modeſty. And this Freedom be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all my ambition, I cannot but aſſure my ſelf of your Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencies gracious Protection and Favour, that may enable
<pb facs="tcp:59434:6"/>me to praiſe God in this way; <hi>That we being delivered out of the hands of our Enemies, <note place="margin">Lu: 1.74.</note> might ſerve him without fear in holineſs and righteouſneſs, before him, all the days of our life.</hi> Praying continually to God, he may be pleaſed to bleſs your Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy with all proſperity, and far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther your holy intentions for the ſpiritual and temporal wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of this Kingdom. I ceaſe to give your Excellency farther trouble, but ſhall ever remain</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Excellencies moſt humble and obedient Servant, And Chaplain, <hi>ANDREW SALL.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:59434:6"/>
            <head>THE PREFACE To my Dear Countrey-men, Friends, and Kinſmen of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communion in IRELAND</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE great Scandal you ſeem to have taken at my withdrawing from the Communion of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Church, and adhering to that of <hi>England,</hi> has occaſioned, I ſhould the more willingly obey the order I had of expoſing to publick view, the account of my proceeding, and motives of my alteration, contained in this <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> which I have preached in the Royal Chappel of <hi>Chriſt-Church</hi> at <hi>Dublin,</hi> deſiring, that ſuch as could
<pb facs="tcp:59434:7"/>not, or would not go thither to hear it, may at their leiſure, and without paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, read it. If my proceedings here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in were indeed a ſcandal, I might juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly fear that <hi>woe</hi> to him that gives it. But mens averſe diſpoſition is apt to term a <hi>ſcandal,</hi> what in it ſelf is an <hi>example.</hi> And I have ground to hope it is ſo with you at preſent in my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern. Certainly it may be called an <hi>example,</hi> and a good one, if you hear the voice of God, not to harden your heart, or ſhut your ears againſt it, though you may prudently examine the calling, and endeavour to be certified whether it be of God. And when you are aſſured it is ſo, to obey your Lord and Maker, not heeding the cryes of the world againſt you, nor the ſuggeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of humane fear or ſhame. So did the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> who hearing that high and honourable calling of God, by the mouth of the Angel <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briel,</hi> did neither harden her heart, nor ſhut her ears againſt it; nor yet did ſhe give a ſudden aſſent, but repli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb facs="tcp:59434:7"/>with a preſſing reaſon, according to the rules of humane Diſcourſe, ſaying, <hi>How ſhall this be, <note place="margin">Lu. 1.34.</note> ſeeing I know not a man?</hi> but convinced with ſuperiour evidences, repreſented by the Angel, ſhe obeyed promptly the will of God, not regarding her former apprehenſion of fear and ſhame. Her example I have followed, I heard the voice of God by ſeveral ways, interiour and exteriour, calling me out of the errours of my former profeſſion. I neither harden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my heart with reſolute obſtinacy, nor gave a haſty aſſent to change: but by prayer and ſtudy of many years, did endeavour to certifie my ſelf of the truth, by all the ways I could imagine fit to find it out; and being at laſt fully convinced, did reſolutely embrace it, and openly declare for it, not heeding the cryes, nor fearing the menaces of paſſion and malice againſt me. If you will not think fit to follow my exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in this kind of proceeding, I hope you will not diſdain to follow that I propoſed of the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary.</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:59434:8"/>If you hear the voice of God, by what mouth or means ſoever it comes, har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den not your hearts, examine and try in God's Name, whether it be really his voice and will, and finding it is ſo, fear not to declare for Chriſt before the World, leſt he may refuſe to own you before his Heavenly Father.</p>
            <p>To perſons thus diſpoſed, and to ſuch onely, I deſire my words or wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to be addreſſed, deeming it labour loſt, to ſpeak or write to any that is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved obſtinately to lye where his Lot was to fall, be it right or wrong. That there ſhould be any ſo careleſs of their greateſt concern, is an object of pity, but of wonder, that their judicious In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructors ſhould teach them to think and do accordingly; perſwading them it is a mortal ſin to admit of any doubt in their belief; that they muſt neither hear nor read any Arguments againſt it; or if they happen to do, it must be with reſolution not to yield or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent to them, be they never ſo demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrative or evident: which is really to
<pb facs="tcp:59434:8"/>deveſt men of rationality, and make Religion a matter of chance, not of council or free election, and ſo undeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving praiſe or reward. They allow to others whom they would gain to their party the uſe of their reaſon and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to hear and examine Arguments propoſed to them, otherwiſe why ſhould they go about to convert them. How then come their own Flock to be exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted from the uſe of this priviledge, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to the reſt of humane kind.</p>
            <p>They wonder that I, by ſo many years learning and teaching Philoſophy and Divinity, in ſeveral famous Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges of <hi>Spain,</hi> ſhould not find out un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til now, on which ſide the truth of Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Religion did ſtand. Which is to wonder, that I could judge better of a debate after hearing both parties, than when I was hearing onely one ſide; to wonder that by ten years of more ſtudy, I ſhould learn more. Which will appear yet a more unreaſonable wonder, if you conſider what St. <hi>Luke</hi> relates of Jeſus Chriſt the Son of God,
<pb facs="tcp:59434:9"/>though of infinite wiſedom, <note place="margin">Lu. 2, 40.</note> that as man he ſeemed to grow more wiſe by age. And ſhall we diſdain to grow more wiſe with more time, and with more light ſent from God?</p>
            <p>They object to me, that I am the firſt of my Family that became Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant: And ſo was St. <hi>Paul</hi> the firſt of his, that became Christian. If I am now in the right, as I am fully ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that I am, I heartily wiſh that my Kinſmen, according to the fleſh, would follow my example, in examining the Truth, and adhering to it,</p>
            <p>They tell me I was unkind and hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted, in forſaking my Friends and Kindred, in diſcomforting and offend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing many Noble Families, at home and abroad, from whom I have received ſingular demonſtrations of Love and Honour. None is more ſenſible of the hardſhip of that caſe than my ſelf. To dye effectively in defence of Truth, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver appeared to me ſo harſh, as to be alienated from my Friends, and to ſee their love turned to hatred, but all
<pb facs="tcp:59434:9"/>that, though heavy, I thought more to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable, than God's anger, which I was to draw upon me, by working againſt my conſcience.</p>
            <p>They ſay I loſt my wits; and well may they ſay it, if for humane reſpects I did take this reſolution: but if for ſuperiour motives of pleaſing God, and ſecuring Eternal Happineſs upon ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ground, I might expect they ſhould rather take it for the greateſt ſhew of wiſedom I could give. The tryal will be to examine the reaſons I give for my reſolution, in the enſuing Diſcourſe, by publick writing, that indifferent perſons may judge which of us ſpeaketh more ſenſe. That I heartily deſire to ſee, provided it be in a modeſt and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious way, with plain and ſolid reaſons grounded upon the Word of God, as becomes Chriſtians and Learned men to ſpeak, and will be fit for clearing the Truth. Shewing wherein my reaſons, againſt their Tenents, examined in this Diſcourſe are deficient<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> or what other reaſons they have for them of more
<pb facs="tcp:59434:10"/>ſtrength, and expect my Anſwer to them. To ſuch Replyes I will liſten willingly, and anſwer ſeriouſly, with reſolution to honour and acknowledge Truth whereſoever I ſee it. If they think I am in an errour, and pretend to win me out of it, this is the way, and not by promiſes, menaces, or ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies; with all I was aſſaulted. To them that came with promiſes, I gave all ſhews of perfect indignation. To the menaces I anſwered with <hi>Suſanna; <note place="margin">Dan. 3.22.</note> It is better for me to fall into your hands, and not to do it, than to ſin in the ſight of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The calumnies are ſo rude, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently falſe, that I need not wiſh more harm to their Forgers, than that they ſhould be known. Such is, to ſay that after reſolving to embrace the Communion of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> I went about to my Friends in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Tipperary,</hi> and collected a great ſum of Money to go over Seas, and then came with it this other way. The un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth of this baſe obloquy, I made evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb facs="tcp:59434:10"/>after diligent enquiry, as is well known to the moſt Reverend, the Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Caſhell,</hi> and to ſeveral other Perſons of Quality.</p>
            <p>I being ſo averſe to ſuch proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that I paſſed by the Houſes of my chief Friends and Kinſmen in that County without taking leave from them, fearing they would offer me any Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney for my Voyage (then intended for <hi>England,</hi> as I have declared to ſome) and onely entred in very few Houſes, where I had ſome concerns to diſpoſe of, and where, by good luck, no Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney was given or offered to me.</p>
            <p>Of the like condition, is the report ſpread here in <hi>Dublin,</hi> that at making my Declaration in the Church of St. <hi>John</hi> at <hi>Caſhell,</hi> before the moſt Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend, the Lord Archbiſhop of that Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and the Right Reverend, the Lord Biſhop of <hi>Waterford,</hi> and a very great Congregation, I was ſtruck dumb, and could not ſpeak a word. And that af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter going in the ſtreet, I fell dead ſuddenly. It were both tedious and
<pb facs="tcp:59434:11"/>rediculous to mention all the Fables they coyn daily, forging things certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo far from my thoughts, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to my inclination, as to put my hand in the fire. I could not but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect this kind of proceeding from them, knowing how much their Writers of greateſt repute, do encourage them to it, ſaying, <hi>it is lawful for a Prieſt, or Reſigious man, to kill any that would offer to divulge grave faults of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, or of his Religion.</hi> And which to me ſeemeth no leſs cruel; <hi>That it is not a grievous ſin, to raiſe falſe Teſtimonies againſt him that would blemiſh one's honour, to bereave him of credit.</hi> If they allow this kind of defence for the honour of every parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, what may expect they will ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſt to deſtroy, or defame, one they ſu ſpect may dimin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſh with his oppoſition, the credit of their whole Religion. I abſtain, at preſent, from quoting the Authours of this Doctrine, not willing to defame the Teachers of ſuch infa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Tenents, until farther occaſion
<pb facs="tcp:59434:11"/>make it neceſſary to ſhew, how oppoſite they be to the Law of God, and the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Chriſt. This kind of defence is a great diſcredit to their cauſe, Truth needeth not ſuch weapons to be drawn for it. <hi>David</hi> ſaith, <note place="margin">Pſa. 16.2.</note> That God needeth not our goods; <hi>Deus meus es, quoniam bonorum meorum non eges.</hi> And if he needs not our goods, ſurely he needs not our evil. Who uſeth theſe means, ſheweth clearly it is not for God he acts; for God refuſeth all ſuch ways.
<note place="margin">Job 13.7.</note> 
               <hi>Will you ſpeak wickedly for God</hi> (ſaith holy <hi>Job</hi>) <hi>and talk de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully for him?</hi> Certainly none of his true Followers will do ſo. It is not the way Christ and his Apoſtles did ſhew us to propagate their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</p>
            <p>Several Perſons that pretended to deſire my ſafety, were employed to fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warn me I ſhould not ſpeak in preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice of the Party I forſook, in terms which might ſeem a threatning, if I did not take that advice. If they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire that I ſhould not raiſe, or blazon
<pb facs="tcp:59434:12"/>the faults of particular perſons or So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties, I am my ſelf totally inclined and fully reſolved to obſerve that rule. But if they expect that I ſhould not ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie my departure from the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Communion, by declaring the exceptions I took againſt their erroneous <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>enents which I could not with approbation of my conſcience embrace: it is a cruel unjuſt demand, and as much as to ſay, I ought not to defend Iruth and my Credit, according to the Law of God and Nature, but permit them to ſtrike at both without reply, to which I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conſent.</p>
            <p>And whereas I underſtand there are malicious gloſſes made upon my Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, falſifying the words of it, to build cavils upon others, ſubſtituted by themſelves. For diſcovery of that impoſture, and manifeſtation of Truth a true Copy of the ſaid Declaration as delivered it in the Church of St <hi>John</hi> at <hi>Caſhell,</hi> is hereto annexed the following Diſcourſe being a fulle<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> explication of what is there ſaid in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral.
<pb facs="tcp:59434:12"/>And that malice may confide leſs in its contrivances, thinking they will not be diſcovered and confuted, I will let it have here a view of its own weakneſs, declaring one of its attempts by way of the foreſaid Declaration.</p>
            <p>Among other tryals made of my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy in my reſolution taken, was a Letter written to me in the moneth of <hi>June</hi> laſt, wherein was advertiſed, that in my Declaration I acknowledged, that <hi>ſome years paſt, I did intend, and reſolve to forſake the</hi> Romiſh <hi>Communion, and adhere to the Church of</hi> England. Contrary to which reſolution, were extant Writings of mine in thoſe times, approving and defending the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the indifferent Reader to peruſe carefully the Declaration, and ſee whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in it he finds mention of a <hi>Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution made ſome years ago, of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking the</hi> Roman <hi>Church?</hi> and he ſhall onely find, that ſome years ago I doubted of the truth of ſome Articles of that Church, but no word of a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution
<pb facs="tcp:59434:13"/>made of ſeparating from it, as truly I never made it, until the firſt day of laſt <hi>May;</hi> and no man living is able to ſay with truth, that he ſaw any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion of mine by word or writing, concerning ſuch a Reſolution, until that day. So this Foundation of that gloſs, being thus evidently falſified, all the breed of that great pregnaney comes to be that writings of mine are extant, wherewith in times paſt, I defended the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. A ſingular diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; as if my name were not to be ſeen, enrolled ſeveral years in the Regiſtry or publick Books of the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamanca,</hi> for Profeſſour of Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies in one of the Colledges, Members of that <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverfity; and my Auditors be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing compoſed of <hi>Spaniſh, French,</hi> and <hi>Iriſh,</hi> my Dictates may not be in many hands, both in this Countrey, and abroad; as if I were not one of the moſt ſrequent and earneſt Diſputers in favour of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, ſince I came to this Land This being generally known, and my ſelf canfeſſing it with
<pb facs="tcp:59434:13"/>repentance of my unfortunate errour therein; what purchaſe do they pretend to make with this acute diſcovery? of one I may probably aſſure them, that the unpaſſionate will judge them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of credit in matters leſs clear, when they pretend to blind my ſelf, and all the Countrey, making us believe, that in my Declaration, extant in ſo many hands as here publiſhed, <hi>I did acknowledge, that ſome years paſt I did intend and reſolve to deſert the</hi> Roman, <hi>and adhere to the Proteſtant Church,</hi> whereas therein is onely ſaid, that ſome years ago I doubted of the truth of ſome <hi>Romiſh</hi> Articles, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>layed to give aſſent againſt them. And any good judgment may ſee, that to doubt of the truth of ſome Articles, may be far enough from concluding up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the untruth of them; and even this later may be yet farther from a reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion upon a total breach, and ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from a Church.</p>
            <p>Herein we ſee paſſion blinded for not to be ſenſible of ſhame, in telling
<pb facs="tcp:59434:14"/>palpable untruths: weakneſs is no leſs diſcovered, in pretending to diſcredit me, with telling, I did in former years approve and defend the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. With this note, St. <hi>Paul</hi> may be brand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, for being zealous one time of the Synagogue, and oppoſing the Goſpel. They ſhould remember, that I live now in a Congregation allowed to read Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, and not ignorant of the gracious Word of God, delivered by the Prophet <hi>Ezekiel;
<note place="margin">Ezek 22.22</note> If the wicked will turn from all his ſins that he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, and keep all my ſtatutes, and do that which is lawful &amp; right he ſhall ſurely live, he ſhall not dye <hi>All his tranſgreſſions that he hath committed, they ſhall not be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned unto him.</hi>
               </hi> If the godly peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple with whom I converſe, make any mention of my former errours, it is to rejoyce at my converſion from them <hi>As there is joy in the preſence of the Angels of God, <note place="margin">Luke. 15.10.</note> over one ſinner that repenteth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To this ſhot by way of menace, wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:59434:14"/>adjoyned another from the ſame hand, pointing at my intention. For they do <hi>not think it a robbery, to make themſelves equal to God,</hi> in ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hearts, and diſcerning intentions. They object to me, that if my intention was to be certified of truth, as I do profeſs, I ſhould have conſulted my doubts with ſome of my Brethren about me. To which I anſwer; Firſt, that I could not judge any of my Brethren living about me, more fit to reſolve me upon theſe points, than <hi>Suarez, Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larmine, Becanus, Stapleton,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, the moſt learned Defenders of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, with whom I was always very much converſant, I would not judge any of them mentioned ſo vain, as to pretend he could give me more ſatisfaction, than the Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of thoſe great Doctors could af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford. Secondly, I ſay, that to try their ſkill, I related very often to the beſt underſtanders about me, my ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral encounters with Learned Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants, their Objections and my An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers.
<pb facs="tcp:59434:15"/>And I never yet met with any that would tell me, I did not anſwer right, or that I needed a ſupply from him to do it. My Learned Oppoſers were wont to ſay, that a man ſo long time exerciſed in School debates, could hardly want an Anſwer to Arguments, but that they ſuſpected I was not my ſelf ſatisfied; and their ſuſpicion there in was not erroneous. I could conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue farther, giving anſwer to others, but to the ſerious Propoſals of my own judgment in the preſence of God, in fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of his truth, I could not reſiſt, and to them I yielded.</p>
            <p>I ſay Thirdly, that many days be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore my Declaration for the Proteſtant Church, I ſignified by Letter and Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage to ſuch as I thought fit to divulg it of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Clergy and Nobility that although I was forced to come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the protection of the moſt Reverend Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Caſhell,</hi> to avoid the popular fury raiſed againſt me; yet I would not declare againſt Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, while any
<pb facs="tcp:59434:15"/>hopes appeared of being ſatisfied in the Exceptions I took againſt the preſent practice of that Church; and being they had among them my Writing, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſaid Exceptions (which in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance are thoſe contained in the enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Diſcourſe) ſo long time as may ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice to have Copies of it, I deſired any that would pretend to reſolve me upon thoſe Exceptions ſhould appear, and that I would give a willing and unpaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate hearing to his reaſons. But none appeared for that purpoſe, nor ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to have a mind to do it. Neither in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed had I reaſon to hope, that any of them could give me ſatisfaction, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo long time, and very carefully ſtudied upon the reaſons, given by the moſt Learned Defenders of their cauſe, and found no ſatisfaction in them: and the rather, that when my Paper came to their hands containing the exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptions I took againſt the <hi>Romiſh</hi> tenents, (but without any mention of ſeparati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) in ſtead of a charitable conference with my ſelf, they ſtirred the people to
<pb facs="tcp:59434:16"/>fury againſt me, ſaying, I was already made Miniſter, and to preach at the Proteſtant Church at <hi>Caſhell</hi> the Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day following: which being a fiction of their own, I told it was ſo in a Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans houſe, where I had notice of that report, without any promiſe made, (much leſs an Oath) that I ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver become a Proteſtant, which was one of the very falſe impoſtures framed againſt me, without fear of God, or ſhame to be found in untruths. For cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly I neither ſaid that, nor had any Queſtion made to me, that would oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion ſaying it.</p>
            <p>But thoſe ſtories ſo enraged the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that from worthy perſons who ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered my ſafety, I had notice given me of menaces made to deſtroy me, or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vey me where I ſhould not appear ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king againſt the <hi>Romiſh</hi> party. As to the former, truly I could hardly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that Christians, Countreymen, and Kinſmen, whom I ſerved, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver offended, and from whom I had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſhews of love and honour, ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend
<pb facs="tcp:59434:16"/>to deſtroy me for following the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of my conſcience; nor that paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion ſhould ſo blind them, that being under a Government diſſatisfied of their Tenents, they ſhould not be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the gracious toleration given to them, but muſt inſult with violence and malice upon ſuch, as following the light of their conſcience do embrace the Religion, eſtabliſhed by the Law and Government which God has put over us.</p>
            <p>As I heartily wiſh, and tender their welfare, I earneſtly deſire they may avoid this foul kind of proceeding, withdraw their ſilly Rythmers, Scoulds, and Forgers of Calumnies, and employ their good wits in examining ſoberly and ſeriouſly) for the Glory of God, manifeſtation of Truth, and edificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the people) the Points I handle in this Diſcourſe; and ſhewing wherein my Arguments againſt their Tenents are defective; or what Arguments they repute of moſt ſtrength for them, and that with Authority of undoubted Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonical
<pb facs="tcp:59434:17"/>Scripture, clear reaſons groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon it, or practice uniform of the Primitive Church. Not by Hyperboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal expreſſions of ſome one or more of Ancient Authours, Rhetorical Flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and Tropical Applications of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, drawing them from their direct genuine meaning, to others different by the help of ſome Figure. At which rate of diſputing, the Alcoran of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homet,</hi> and the Talmud of the <hi>Jews,</hi> may be defended as plauſibly, as the Council of <hi>Trent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The God of Peace, and his Son Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, who bequeathed it for inheritance to his Diſciples, make us appear to be of them, living in peace and charity to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in this Life, that ſo we may joyn to praiſe him in Life everlaſting. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:59434:17"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Mr.</hi> ANDREW SALL<hi>'s</hi> Declaration, made in the Church of St. <hi>John,</hi> in the City of <hi>Caſhell,</hi> the Fourth Sunday after <hi>Eaſter, May</hi> the Seventeenth; preſent the moſt Reverend THOMAS, Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Caſhell;</hi> and the Right Reverend, HUGH Lord Biſhop of <hi>Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terford.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>VVHEREAS I <hi>Andrew Sall,</hi> have been born and bred in the Communion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholick Church, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed a Religious Life, and compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my Courſes of Philoſophy and Divinity in Colledges of the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>JESUS</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> and was imployed in teaching of the ſaid
<pb facs="tcp:59434:18"/>Faculties many years, I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, that ſince, by occaſion of this Function, I applyed my ſelf to a ſtructer enquiry and examining of matters, and by frequent reading of the Holy Scriptures, Fathers, Councils, and Hiſtories of the Church, my knowledge was far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered, and my judgment ripened, I began to doubt of the truth of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Articles, introduced by the Vſe and Authority of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, repugnant to human rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and not warranted by Divine Writ; as Tranſubſtantiation, In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, Purgatory, Worſhip of Images, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> yet ſmothered my ſcruples, while I was in <hi>Spain,</hi> partly fearing the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of that Countrey againſt Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers of their Tenents, partly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muſed with a ſuppoſition, that the Church and Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> were infallible in their Decrees touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Faith, and ſo may ſtand with ſecurity to their declarations. But
<pb facs="tcp:59434:18"/>having arrived to this Countrey, diſputed often and cloſely of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, with ſeveral Perſons emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in Learning and Integrity, but principally with the moſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Father in God (and mine truly in Chriſt) his Grace, <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Caſhell</hi> preſent, who mindful of the duty of a good Paſtor, did procure to bring into his Fold this ſtraying ſheep, with an unſpeakable conſtancy, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>defatigable charity, ſuffering for ſix years of continual battery my obſtinate reſiſtance, till at laſt, by means of his ſolid doctrine, and of the example of his pious and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right Life, (to the glory of God be I permitted to ſay thus much here) the Lord was pleaſed to give me a more clear ſight of the errours I was in; yet a full aſſent I delay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to give, partly fearing, that the weakneſs I felt, might be of my capacity, rather than of the cauſe I maintained, partly frighted with
<pb facs="tcp:59434:19"/>the confuſions and dangers I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived might wait upon my deſert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Communion, and ſo betook my ſelf to a muſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent ſtudy of the caſe, leaving no ſtone unmoved to quiet the trouble of my conſcience, reading with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different eyes, the beſt Writers on both ſides. And though I heartily wiſhed to find the cauſe I hitherto maintained, juſtified, for not to run into the terrible inconveniences, which human conſiderations repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented to me in a change; yet aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Divine grace, and taking for rule of my Actions, the Service and Will of God, and the Intereſt of Eternity, I reſolved conſtantly to adhere to the Party, which with better ground, would render me ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure of this higher Emolument; when being in theſe conſiderations, ſuddenly iſſued out our Sovereign Lord the King's Proclamation for baniſhing the <hi>Roman</hi> Clergy, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with I ſaw my ſelf betwixt two
<pb facs="tcp:59434:19"/>Extremities, either to continue far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the Countrey, with my am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biguities, in diſobedience to my So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign's commands, or to go into <hi>Spain,</hi> and there be forced to preach and practiſe Doctrines my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence did not approve of; and for a ſpeedy reſolution, after earneſt pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to God, for the aſſiſtance of his Divine light, in ſo weighty a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, I penned down for better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration, the reaſons I did hear, read, and conceive, againſt the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Tenents controverted. I did alſo carefully peruſe, and ſeriouſly reflect upon the <hi>39.</hi> Articles, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons, and Liturgy of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and all conſidered well, I did conclude the way of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to be ſafer for my Salvation, than that of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. Wherefore I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to declare, as I do hereby ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly and in my heart, without any equivocation, or mental reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, in the preſence of God, and
<pb facs="tcp:59434:20"/>this Congregation declare, that I do give my full and free aſſent to the <hi>39.</hi> Articles of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for holy and wiſe, &amp; groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon the infallible Word of God, acknowledging the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Tenents againſt them, to be falſe and ſuperſtitious, eſpecially that of Tranſubſtantiation, as forcing upon Chriſtians a belief of mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrous miracles, repugnant to hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man reaſon, and not grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Divine Teſtimony, nor neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry either for verifying Chriſt's Words in the Inſtitution of this Bleſſed Sacrament, or for the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of it; not for verifying the words, whereas Chriſt ſaith in the like tenour, that he is the true vine, without real alteration in his Perſon, or in the vine; nor for the effects of the holy Sacrament, Chriſt being able to annex unto the receiving of Bread and Wine, what ſpiritual Grates he pleaſeth, without alteration of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb facs="tcp:59434:20"/>as he doth afford the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Grace of Regeneration in the Waters of Baptiſm, without al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration in the ſubſtance of the Water.</p>
            <p>And leſt an imagination of ſome temporal or ſiniſtrous intention in this my Declaration, upon the preſent conjuncture may hinder the ſpiritual benefit which ſouls may reap by it, I have grave teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies to ſhew, and did already ſhew them to my renowned Lord Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop his Grace, which aſſureth I did enjoy in <hi>Spain</hi> (and may now enjoy with more advantage going thither, upon the account I was to go) ſuch degree of honour and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modity, as poſſibly I may not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect elſewhere; ſo as looking upon a Voyage thither, continuing my former Profeſſion, nothing occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to my mind but pleaſure, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe, and honour; and turning my eyes upon my preſent reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, mountains of croſſes and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers
<pb facs="tcp:59434:21"/>did fright me. But in this perplexity, I have choſen rather to ſuffer croſſes here with ſarisfaction of conſcience than to enjoy honours that other way, accompanied with the tortures of a checking conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, and the unworthineſs of a diſſembling life.</p>
            <p>Wherefore I humbly beſeech your Grace, that I may be admitted into the Communion of this Church, and that I may be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved for my ſo long continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance in Errour, reſiſting the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>werful Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ling of God, which granted, I hope by the Grace of Almighty God, aſſiſting me, that I ſhall never withdraw my ſelf; for farther confirmation of all this I have hereunto ſubſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed my Name,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Andrew Sall.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59434:21"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>St. MAT. xxiv. 15, 16, 17, 18.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>When ye therefore ſhall ſee the abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of deſolation, ſpoken of by <hi>Daniel</hi> the prephet, ſtand in the holy place, (whoſo readeth let him underſtand) Then let them which be in <hi>Judea</hi> flee into the mountains. Let him which is on the houſe top, not come down to take any thing out of his houſe; neither let him which is in the field, return back to take his clothes.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg>N all occaſions I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it to be the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of a Preacher to ſearch diligently after the genuine and direct meaning of the word of God he takes in hand to expound; that grounding his diſcourſes upon it,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59434:22"/>rather than upon private fancie, they may carry more weight for the benefit of ſouls. But when the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Text doth warn us of this duty, and exhorteth to the right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of it ſelf, as ours at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent doth <hi>(whoſe readeth let him un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand)</hi> then certainly we have a ſpecial obligation of ſearching care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully for the right ſenſe of it: which I have endeavoured to do; and found three ſeveral opinions among ancient and modern Interpreters, touching that <hi>Abomination of Deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation ſtanding in the Holy place,</hi> mentioned in our Text. The firſt opinion, followed by St. <hi>Jerome,</hi> is, that by this Abomination of Deſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, may be underſtood the Image of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> which <hi>Pilate</hi> ſet up in the Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> Or the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the Emperor <hi>Adrian,</hi> which he affirmeth to have ſtood in the moſt ſacred place of the Temple, the <hi>holy of holies</hi> to his own time; which to the people of God was
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59434:22"/>moſt abominable, rendered the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple deſolate and void of Divine prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes; the faithful deſerting the City and Temple, that they might not be partakers of the prophane Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try practiſed in it; as our Saviour councelleth in the words of our Text. The ſecond Opinion follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by very learned Interpreters, and attributed to St. <hi>Chryſoſtom,</hi> is, that by this Abomination is under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the <hi>Roman</hi> Army under <hi>Titus,</hi> coming to beſiege <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and ready to fill the City with their Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, bearing in them the Image of <hi>Caeſar</hi> and his Eagle, which to the <hi>Jews</hi> were Abominable and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane. The third Opinion follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Gloſs Interlineal, is, that the foreſaid words of our Text do relate to the times of Antichriſt,
<note place="margin">2 Theſſ. 2.3.</note> when that <hi>man of ſin</hi> ſhall be revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,
<note place="margin">Dan. 11.36. 2 Theſſ. 2.4.</note> 
               <hi>who ſhall exalt himſelf and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnifie himſelf above every God, and who oppoſeth and exalteth himſelf above all that is called God,</hi> as St.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59434:23"/>
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith. At whoſe appearance our Saviour exhorteth the faithful to ſhun the place where they ſee it pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant. All which three Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, though different in expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, do concur to the ſame purpoſe of our ſpiritual inſtruction, and will contribute to the right grounding the Points I intend to raiſe upon our Text to that end. The following words of our Text, do ſet forth the haſt and diligence wherewith our Saviour would have the Faithful to ſhun the place infected with that Evil. <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Gerſon. Tract. in Magnifi cat. pag.</hi> 97.</note> The Buildings of <hi>Judea</hi> had commonly plain Roofs to walk up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as <hi>Gerſon</hi> relateth: now who ſhould happen to be on ſuch Roofs, is councelled by our Saviour not to ſtay for going by the ordinary way, nor regard the ordering of his houſe; nor he that ſhould be in the field re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to take his clothes, but haſten his flight with all the ſpeed he can; being better to loſe all, than to loſe his ſoul.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:59434:23"/>
            <p>Our Text being explain'd thus, the firſt Point of my diſcourſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it, will be to juſtifie the Councel of our Saviour; that if we ſhould ſee any of thoſe three Abominations declared by the three Opinions rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, Idolatry, Prophane violence, or Antichriſtian impiety, predominant in any Church or Congregation, we are to ſhun it with all ſpeed; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out regarding ceremonies or compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ances with men, or the loſs of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane intereſt or honour. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond is to declare, that I ſaw, (and by what means I came to ſee) all theſe three kind of Abominations practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. The third ſhall be to conclude from theſe Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſes, that the reſolution I took of withdrawing ſpeedily from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of that Church, when I was convinced of ſuch corruptions to ſway in it, was Juſt and Neceſſary: and therefore undeſerving ſo great an offence and ſcandal as is taken at it by the generality of my former Brethren.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:59434:24"/>
               <head>Firſt Point.</head>
               <p>As it is clear that Heaven is of more value than a piece of the Earth, Everlaſting Glory, than a ſhort joy of this Miſerable mortal Life, the Favour and Grace of God than that of Men: ſo clear (and not needing tedious proofs) is the Firſt Point propoſed of our diſcourſe; that if we ſhould ſee a Church in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with corruptions inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtent with the true worſhip and ſervice of God, we are to quit it with all ſpeed and diligence, not heeding mens diſcontents, nor any earthly intereſt. But why was our Saviour ſo earneſt with his own Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples that they ſhould quit the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and the Fertil Fields of <hi>Judea</hi> upon ſuch an emer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencie, and flee to barren moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains? might it not be expected from their conſtant Faith and fervent Piety, improved in the School of Chriſt, enriched with the Heavenly dew of healthful Doctrine dayly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:59434:24"/>dropping upon them from his Divine lips, that in midſt of the Idolatry and Prophaneſs of the <hi>Romans</hi> they would preſerve themſelves pure and unſpotted as the Fiſh in the Sea with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reliſhing the ſalt of it? Nay further, may it not be expected that by their Doctrine and example of their Holy Life, the ſores of <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> may be healed and the inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants of it reduced to a better Life? No; of their amendment there was no hope, becauſe their hearts were hardened as that of <hi>Pharao,</hi> and their diſeaſe incurable, which did encreaſe with the very remedies of it; their Stomacks ſo corrupt, that they turned the moſt healthful food into Poyſon: their minds were ſo perverſe, that they abhorred their Cure and killed their Phyſitians: ſo our Saviour declared of them in the Chapter precedent to that of our Text, the 23 of St. <hi>Mathew</hi> put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting them in mind that their Fathers before them did ſo, themſelves did
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59434:25"/>ſo at preſent, and would do the ſame in the future. The doleful words of our Saviour to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe are much to be remarked. <note place="margin">St. <hi>Math.</hi> 23 <hi>v.</hi> 29 31.32.39.</note> 
                  <hi>Wo to you Scribes and Phariſees Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites. Ye be witneſſes unto your ſelves that ye are the children of them which killed the Prophets. Fill up then the meaſure of your Fathers. Behold I ſend unto you Prophets and wiſe men and Scribes and ſome of them ye ſhall kill and crucifie, and ſome of them ſhall ye ſcourge in your Synagogues, and perſecute them from City to City: That upon you may come all the right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eous Bloud ſhed upon the Earth</hi> &amp;c. The People of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> being thus given over to a reprobate obſtinacie, what hopes could our Saviours Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples entertain of healing them?</p>
               <p>Neither could they prudently hope to be ſafe themſelves in ſo great and general corruption. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> thought it one and the ſame thing to live in a corrupted company and be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted himſelf: <hi>Wo is me,</hi> ſaid he,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59434:25"/>
                  <hi>For I am undone, becauſe I am a man of unclean Lips, and I dwell in the midſt of a People of unclean lips.</hi> Whereupon St. <hi>Jerome</hi> ſaith that the former part of the Text was a declaration of the later; and to ſay he lived with a people of unclean lips was as much as to ſay he was himſelf of unclean lips: <note place="margin">St. <hi>Hier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. ep.</hi> 1. <hi>ad Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſcum.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>hoc in Peca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti ac miſeriae parte ducit Propheta ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitans in medio populi polluta labia habentis.</hi> So powerful is the influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of bad company that the beſt of men are apt to be ſpotted if not corrupted with it! Even Angels it ſeems may not be ſafe from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagions of ſuch neighbourhood. In the firſt Chapter of <hi>Geneſis</hi> is relat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that <hi>God divided the light from the darkneſs.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gen. 1. <hi>Rupert. li.</hi> 1. <hi>in Geneſ. c.</hi> 13.</note> By which words <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pert</hi> underſtands how God ſeparated the good Angels from the Bad; and inquiring further what may be the motive of this ſeperation, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwereth, it was, that the Good Angels may not be perverted by
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59434:26"/>the company of the Bad. How? are Angels Subject to ſuch mutabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities? Is it not their nature to have liberty in their firſt election, but that once made, to ſtick immove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably to the ſide they adhered to? <note place="margin">
                     <hi>St. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> 1. <hi>p. q.</hi> 64. <hi>art.</hi> 2.</note> So Divines do teach commonly in Schools. But ſuch is the Power of bad company, that it will make e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Angels to forget their nature and be perverted with the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe.</p>
               <p>We have another fair ſhew of this verity in the 10th. Chapter of St. <hi>Luke,</hi> V. 18. where our Saviour, in teſtimony of his Divine power, <note place="margin">Luke 10.18.</note> tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth, that he <hi>beheld Sathan as light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning fall from Heaven.</hi> And what ſingularity appears in that? did not the Angels, and all the world, ſee the ſame? <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rupent. l</hi> 1 <hi>de victoria Verbi Dei. c.</hi> 13.</note> yea, ſaith <hi>Rupert;</hi> but with fear and danger; only Chriſt the Son of God, could behold that ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctacle with ſecurity. <hi>Solus iſte vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debat ſecurus ſui; Angeli autem vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunt in magno terrore poſiti.</hi> So ſtrong
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59434:26"/>and active is the venom of a bad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, and ſcandalous company, that even thoſe pure Angelical ſpirits could not be ſecure from the conta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion of it, in the opinion of this lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Father; only Chriſt could be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold with vafety the diſmal fall of Sathan; <hi>ſolus iſte videbat ſecurus ſui.</hi> Truſt not in your virtue, build no confidence upon your good nature; bad company will corrupt virtue, and pervert nature.</p>
               <p>This fatal contagious influence of companies, juſtifieth the practice I find in nations of cenſuring every ones temper by the company he fancies. A <hi>Spaniſh</hi> proverb reduced to <hi>Engliſh,</hi> ſays, <hi>Tell me with whom thou walkeſt, and I will tell thee who thou art.</hi> Noble men who tender your repute, Chriſtians who regard your welfare and ſalvation, take heed to what company you adhere. And this doctrine being ſo impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant for all; I will confirm it fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with the famous caſe of that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:59434:27"/>prodigal ſon, ſet down in the 15th. chapter of St. <hi>Luke;</hi> who having la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhed away his ſubſtance, with rio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous living in a forreign countrey,
<note place="margin">Luke 15.15.</note> he joyned himſelf to a Citizen, who employed him in feeding his ſwine; <hi>and he would fain have filled his belly with the husks that the ſwine did eat.</hi> How ſo? that delicate youth, who loathed the plentiful fare of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers houſe, now fancy the huſks that ſwine did eat? Is that a proper food for a man, and ſuch a man? no; but the company of ſwine made him put off his own nature, and wear theirs. <hi>And when he came to himſelf,</hi> ſo followeth the Text. What? did he leave himſelf? yes, ſaith ingenious <hi>Peter Chryſologus, à ſe migrat &amp; tranſit in beſtiam;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſol. Ser.</hi> 2.</note> living with beaſts, he left himſelf, and tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned beaſt. That is the ordinary ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of bad company, to turn into its own condition, the nature of ſuch as adhere to it. To preſume the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, is to pretend to a miracle, and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:59434:27"/>tempt God. It were indeed a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle, and a ſingular one, that a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon living in a bad company, ſhould not conform to it. Our Saviour, to confirm his Doctrine with an uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trolable miracle againſt the obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate <hi>Jews,</hi> who condemned, as Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceries, his other miraculous works; got innocent children to blaze his glory in the Temple of <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> according to the Prophet <hi>David,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Mat. 21.16.</note> in the eighth Pſalm: <hi>Out of the mouths of babes and ſucklings thou haſt perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted praiſe.</hi> This miracle wrought deeply upon the <hi>Jews,</hi> and confirmed them in the belief of the others pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding; as St. <hi>Matthew</hi> relates. <note place="margin">St. <hi>Mat.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 19.</note> 
                  <hi>And when the chief Prieſts and Scribes ſaw the wonderful things that he did, and the children crying in the Temple, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Hoſanna to the Son of</hi> David, <hi>they were ſore diſpleaſed.</hi> What made them take more notice of theſe inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Elegies of the children, than of the other wonders he wrought? <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>Euthymius</hi> gl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſing upon this paſſage,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59434:28"/>anſwers, that in other occaſions they ſuſpected Chriſt might have delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded their eyes with appearances of things not really exiſting; but that their own children, bred by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and living among them, ſhould break out into Elogies of one they ſaw ever contemned and revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by them; was a miracle they knew not how to controll: That ears continually beaten with calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies and opprebries againſt Chriſt, ſhould entertain any favourable opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of him, was a wonder, which malice and envy it ſelf could not ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect. So ſtrange it is, that any ſhould not act according to the tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the company he lives in! A wonder paſſing all wonders! Such is the influence, bad company hath over minds adhering to it! And herewith I conclude the firſt Point of my Diſcourſe; how juſtly our Saviour, in the words of our Text, was ſo earneſt in exhorting his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to ſhun the Abominations of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59434:28"/>
                  <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> given over to corruption and reprobate obſtinacy, that they might not be perverted by them; and that if we ſhould ſee any of thoſe three Abominations declared by the three Opinions of Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, related in the opening of our Text, that is to ſay, Idolatry, Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or Impiety, or all three, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in a Church or Congregation, we are to ſhun it with all ſpeed and diligence.</p>
               <p>Now I will proceed to the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Point propoſed of my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe; which is, to declare how I ſaw, and by what means God was pleaſed to let me ſee, that all theſe three abominations are generally practiſed in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, as it ſtands at preſent; to wit Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie in their Manner of Worſhip. Cruelty in their conduct of Souls and Antichriſtian Impiety in extolling men above God: That ſo my rece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding from the Communion of It, may be juſtified as no more, nor o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59434:29"/>than a dutiful obedience to the Councel of Chriſt, declared in our Text. But before I enter into this Point, I deſire my judicious hearers not to conceive I come here to ſcold or Inſult upon my former Brethren of the <hi>Roman</hi> Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I may not hate Them without hating my ſelf; my fleſh and blood and deareſt friends being among them; with tender compaſſion I lament their Errour. I could not in piety abandon the Mother at whoſe breſt I ſucked the Belief of a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian; if with tears or ſweat I could hope to waſh away the ſtains, which corruption of time has caſt upon her face, once fair and glorious: but ſeeing her diſeaſe appears both in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curable and contagious, I was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to a divorce. Mean faults could not give a juſt cauſe to it; they muſt be grievous ones, which I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not declare without giving them their own names; the ſame our Text and declaration of it puts into
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:59434:29"/>my mouth, for juſt cauſe of the like ſeperation, Idolatrie, Cruelty, Impie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. How I came to perceive the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Practiſe of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church to be guilty of theſe faults I will endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to declare with the brevity and ſincerity duty requires, being to ſpeak in ſo Illuſtrious an Auditory.</p>
               <p>Gods Providence leading me in my younger years to the Schools of greateſt credit in <hi>Spain;</hi> and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſo that having compleated in them my courſes of Philoſophy and Divinity, I ſhould be imployed ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years in teaching the ſame Facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; The exerciſe of thoſe Reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sciences joyned with my own Genius not fit for Pythagoras his School (where <hi>ipſe dixit</hi> was the rule, and knowledge muſt be taken upon credit of the Maſter) got me a habit of demanding reaſon for the belief of Doctrines propoſed. This, aſſiſted by frequent reading of Holy Scriptures, Fathers, Councels and Hiſtories of the Church made me
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:59434:30"/>doubt of the Truth of ſeveral Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents introduced by the uſe or Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant (in my eſteem) to common reaſon, and not warranted by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine teſtimony to captivate my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding to the belief of them. Of the Truth of Holy Scriptures, of the Apoſtles Creed, of that of <hi>Nice</hi> and <hi>Athanaſius</hi> I never doubted. Therein I acknowledged the Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gift of Faith received in the Holy Sacrament of Baptiſm; and lifting my heart and eyes to Heaven, gave thanks to God for this Soveraign be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit in thoſe words of the Pſalm: <note place="margin">Pſal. 4. v. 6.</note> 
                  <hi>Signatum eſt ſuper nos lumen vultûs tui Domine:</hi> Thou haſt lifted upon us, O Lord, and printed in our hearts the light of thy countenance. With<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which, certainly an underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing accuſtomed to ſearch exactly into the nature of things, their Eſſential conſtitutes, the proportion of cauſes with effects, and to meaſure by theſe rules the credibility of them, would
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59434:30"/>never give ſo free and eaſie aſſent to the ineffable myſteries of Trinity and Unity in the Divine nature, of the Incarnation, Reſurrection, Aſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt our Saviour, of the Deſcent of the Holy Ghoſt in tongues of fire upon the Apoſtles, and other myſteries contained in Holy Scripture and the Creeds.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide the reluctancy I found in aſſenting to thoſe Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, as oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite to other Chriſtian Congregations, was to me an occaſion of ſuſpecting they might not be grounded upon Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine inſtitution: all my underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was turmoiled reflecting upon the prodigious Doctrine of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation; alone ſufficient to fright rational believers from the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Communion. By it we are required to believe that when the Prieſt pronounces thoſe few Latin words: <hi>Hoc eſt Corpus me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um,</hi> This is my Body, minding what he ſays, the ſubſtance of all
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59434:31"/>the bread he lays before him, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed in a moment, and inſtead of it, our Saviour Jeſus is placed under that figure of bread perſonally and corporally: A wonder, though a dayly one, yet far ſurpaſſing that other which once happened in the world, when God hearkning to the voice of <hi>Joſhua;</hi> made the Sun and Moon ſtand, till he compleated his Victory againſt the Enemy invading <hi>Gibeon.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Joſh. 10.12.</note> And to ſupport this won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, a great number of others moſt ſtupendious, are chained to it. As Firſt, that thoſe accidents of white and round remaining, do ſubſiſt without any ſubſtance to reſt upon; a thing repugnant to their nature, and to all humane underſtanding. Secondly, that the ſame accidents being converted either into vermin by corruption, or into fleſh and bloud by nutrition, in him that eats them, ſhould produce a ſubſtance; which is, to give what they have not; a thing ſurpaſſing all kind of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:59434:31"/>power. Thirdly, that a proper well proportion'd body, as that of our Saviour, glorious in Heaven, muſt come down and be fitted to every Wafer, and to every the leaſt crumb of them. Fourthly, that the ſame Body muſt lye, ſit, or ſtand, or however, be, in a hundred thouſand places at the ſame time. All theſe monſtrous miracles, and more, we muſt ſwallow, to ſupport that myſtery, in ſpight of all reaſon to the contrary, without any perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Text of Scripture to ground it upon, (nay, many Texts oppoſing it, as we ſhall hereafter declare) and no neceſſity urging to it, either for ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifying the words of our Saviour in the inſtitution of this bleſſed Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or for the effects of it:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>St.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.15.</note> Not for verifying the words; ſeeing our Saviour in the ſame tenor ſaid, <hi>I am the true vine,</hi> without any alteration, either in his Perſon, or in the Vine. And St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of his <hi>Corinthians, <note place="margin">2 Cor. 12 27.</note> ye are the Body of Chriſt,</hi> yet mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:59434:32"/>no converſion of ſubſtances. Nor for the effects of the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; Chriſt being able to convey, with the worthy receiving of Bread and Wine, what ſpiritual graces he pleaſeth, without any ſubſtantial al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration in the Elements; as in the Waters of Baptiſm, he affordeth the ſoveraign grace of Regeneration without any alteration in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Water.</p>
               <p>The like repugnance I felt, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving their prodigious Doctrine of Indulgences, Purgatory, Worſhip of Saints and Images, and other Points controverted with them; but ſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther'd my doubts while in <hi>Spain;</hi> partly fearing the ſeverity of that Countrey, in proceeding againſt Oppoſers of their Doctrine; partly amuſed with the ſuppoſition, that the Church and Pope of <hi>Rome</hi> were Infallible in their Decrees, touching matters of Faith, and ſo might ſtand with ſecurity to their Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. And finally perſwaded by
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:59434:32"/>my Catechiſts, that it was a mortal Sin to admit willingly even a doubt in Matters of Faith. A terrible yoke, reaching to the thoughts of the heart; but conducent to their purpoſe of keeping in their people by right or wrong. With theſe Generalities, I quieted in ſome ſort my mind, while I could ſee none that would ſeriouſly oppoſe thoſe Tenents, nor know the Arguments againſt them, but by relation of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Writers, faſhioning them ſo as they might better receive their ſtroke. For though by occaſion of my Employment of teaching con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies in the Univerſity of <hi>Sala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manca</hi> ſome years, I had a Licence from the Inquiſitor General of <hi>Spain,</hi> to read prohibited Books, yet the Prohibition was ſo ſevere, that I could never come by any Book of their Oppoſers.</p>
               <p>But Divine Providence leading me to this Countrey, I met with perſons of excellent wiſedom, and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59434:33"/>great integrity; who in cloſe and ſerious Diſputes, gave me a different light and help to find out the truth. The chiefeſt of all was, the Moſt Reverend Father in God, <hi>Thomas</hi> Lord Archbiſhop of <hi>Caſhell,</hi> who at his coming to that See, having no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of me, and pittying I ſhould con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in errours, ſought carefully af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter me; and finding me out, with admirable zeal and great dexte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, dictated by Chriſtian cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, ſet upon me with ſolid Arguments of Holy Scripture, Councels, Fathers and Hiſtories; and gave me to view ſeveral learned Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors repreſenting the Errours of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church in all the points controverted; to which I liſtened the more willingly becauſe I ſaw a vein of Charity and Zeal of Union among Chriſtians run through all his diſcourſes, acknowledging the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to be a part of the Catholick Church, though not the Catholick Church, (as they ſpeak,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:59434:33"/>excluding other Chriſtian Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations from that honourable Title) reverencing what in them was good, as the belief of Scripture, and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Creeds, the Practice of Devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Piety, and onely reprov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Superſtructures of Erroneous Practiſes introduced contrary to the Inſtitution of Chriſt and Stile of the Primitive Church: entertaining a charitable hope of the Salvation of many of them that went on with ſimplicity of heart and blameleſs ignorance of the Errours they were bred in.</p>
               <p>All which ſympathizing with my own temper and dictates, in relation to all Chriſtian Congregations, got in my mind a ſpecial reſpect and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to his reaſons. I replied to them with ſincerity and liberty, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the principles I was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in: Where a clear Text or preſſing reaſon was deficient, I ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pealed, as to a Sanctuary, to the Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility of the Church; that in
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59434:34"/>things ſurpaſſing our comprehenſion we were to captivate our under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding to the obedience of Faith propoſed to us by the Church of God.</p>
               <p>To ſecure this refuge and have it in a readineſs, I framed to my ſelf, and propoſed to his Grace, this kind of Demonſtration: That by natural evidences, I was convinced there was a God of infinite Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, wiſedom and power; That to theſe attributes it belonged, he ſhould provide for Man-kind means for obtaining their end of everlaſting bliſs. That by revealed Oracles common to all Chriſtians I believed he ſent down his Son Jeſus Chriſt for this purpoſe in humane nature, and to ſhew by his Example and Doctrine a ſure way to eternal hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs. And providing not only for the age he lived in, but for all times to come; he left upon earth a Church furniſhed with convenient Laws for the foreſaid end. And whereas he
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:59434:34"/>foretold himſelf, that in future times there ſhould ariſe Hereſies and Controverſies, (as it is the nature of men) it became his wiſedom and goodneſs to appoint a viſible Judge, with infallible aſſiſtance of the Holy Ghoſt, to determine all Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies emergent; which Judge was no other than the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor of St. <hi>Peter;</hi> to whoſe defini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions therefore we ought to ſtand, and ſo quiet our minds.</p>
               <p>The former part of this Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration had a grateful acceptance with his Grace, as being rationally and Chriſtianly principled, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing averſe to Piety; till coming to the later Propoſition, <hi>That it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came the wiſedom and goodneſs of Chriſt to appoint a viſible Judge In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible upon Earth, to determine Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies:</hi> He replied mildly, we had reaſon to go warily in cenſuring the wiſedom and goodneſs of God, if this or that thing ſeeming to us ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient, were not done in the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:59434:35"/>of the World: for who can pretend to know the depth of the wiſedom and knowledg of God; <note place="margin">Rom. 11.33.</note> 
                  <hi>to ſearch into his judgments, and find out his ways?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This moſt rational advertiſement took deep root in my heart, ever thirſty of reaſon, and open to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it: Neither did the modeſty of the Propoſer diminiſh, but rather augment the weight of it. It was in truth the firſt ſhock that touched me to the quick, ſtriking upon the very root of that Engine of Infallibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity I leaned upon. Reflecting up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the matter in my ſolitudes, I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the weakneſs of the ground I built upon; I ſaw, that in like manner we may ſay, it belongeth to the goodneſs, wiſedom, and power of God, not to permit that his Holy Law ſhould be tranſgreſſed by vile creatures, and his ſupreme dread Majeſty offended by deſpicable ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine; Nor that Paſtors of Souls, (eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially the <hi>Roman</hi> Pope, deemed a
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59434:35"/>Vice-God upon Earth) ſhould fall into errours, and ſcandalize, with wicked life, the people: And, alas! it is but too well known, he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits this. Shall we therefore wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in the Opinion of his goodneſs, power, and wiſedom? God forbid. Why then ſhould we think it a fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ure in his providence, or goodneſs, if, beſides Holy Scriptures, abound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in all light and Heavenly Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, to ſuch as are not wilfully blind, he did not appoint ſome viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Judge univerſal for our directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaying, <note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.16.17.</note> that <hi>Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures are able to make us wiſe unto ſalvation, that the man of God may be perfect, throughly furniſhed unto all good works.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That Foundation alledging the neceſſity of a Judge viſible, univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal, and Infallible, being thus weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, I proceeded to examine what right the Pope or Church of <hi>Rome</hi> could pretend to ſuch infallibility, the ſupport of all their Incredible
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59434:36"/>Doctrine. And, firſt, the very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtancy of their pretence to this priviledge, and great diſſention of their Authors in aſſerting it, was to me a main reaſon of ſuſpecting the truth of all, and a concluding argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that they cannot be certain of having it. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide Bel</hi> l. 4. <hi>de Rom. Pont. c.</hi> 2.</note> For ſome will have the Pope himſelf alone, as Pope, or as teaching from his chair, to have this Infallibility of Doctrine. Others will not allow it him, but in conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction with a Council, either general, or particular of Cardinals and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines. Others only attribute it to him in a General Council. Others neither ſeparately nor conjunctly, and will only allow the Church Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal to be Infallible. And finally, others of the moſt Learned affirm even the Church Univerſal,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>S. Tho. Turre <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>mata. Alphon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ct<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o apud Candi</hi> 4 <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> c.</hi> 4 <hi>concl.</hi> 2.</note> to be capable of a Material Errour by Probable Ignorance, though not of a Formal and Heretical one: which in ſubſtance is to allow the Church no more Infallibility than <hi>Origen,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:59434:36"/>Tertullian,</hi> or any other particular true Chriſtian Believer hath, though ſubject to errors; (which Opinion if extended to make the Univerſal Church fallible even in Points Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential to ſaluation, is falſe). And upon ſo great an uncertainty of their Infallibility, they will have us to build a certain Infallible Belief of all they pleaſe to teach us; which is, to build a houſe incapable of falling, upon a ſandy and ruinous Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>Now for their grounds for this pretended Infallibility; what is their warrant for it? Divine Scripture they ſay, for who but God could give ſuch a Priviledge? and what warrant have they for believing he Scripture ſaying ſo to be Divine and Infallible? The Infallible Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the Church, ſay they again; their own <hi>Roman</hi> Church they mean. So they believe the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture is Infallible, becauſe the <hi>Roman</hi> Church doth teſtifie it; and this
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:59434:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>Church to be Infallible, becauſe the Scriptures Teſtimony is for it. A circle in reaſoning, which Logicians would hiſs out of their Schools. Neither may <hi>Becan</hi>'s eſcape avail him, that they deal with Chriſtians who believe the Scripture: for no Chriſtian, but ſuch as they will make blind, can believe that there is any Scripture favouring their caſe in this particular, without clipping or corrupting it to ſerve their pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. For example, Their main pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar for this Infallibility, fetcht out of the 24th. chapter of St. John, <note place="margin">John 14.16.</note> 
                  <hi>I will pray the Father, and he ſhall give you another Comforter, that he may abide with you for ever, even the Spirit of truth.</hi> Their own Diſciples, who ordinarily know no more of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, than what they are pleaſed to ſhew to them for their ſeveral purpoſes; may think that Text to be pertinent for their pretentions. But who will take the liberty to read the Context before and after,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:59434:37"/>will clearly find out, that the very ſame Text deſtroyeth their whole deſign, and taketh away all certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Holy Ghoſt his aſſiſtance, for rendring their Decrees Infallible. The Text reſtored to its integrity ſaith thus in their own Bible: <hi>If ye love me keep my commandments, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mundus, id eſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manens amator mundi, cum quo nurquam eſt amor Dei.</hi> Gloſſ. in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terlin. <hi>Non ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituales oculos quibus Spiritum ſanctum videant mu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>i ama<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>res,</hi> Gloſſ. ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria.</note> and I will ask my Father, and he ſhall give you another Paraclete, that he may abide with you for ever, even the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of Truth, whom the World cannot receive.</hi> By the firſt words you may ſee this to be a conditional promiſe, limited to ſuch as love God, and keep his Commandments: by the later words you ſee worldly and ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful men expreſly excluded from re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving that gracious aſſiſtance of the Spirit of Truth; therefore to be ſure that the Pope and his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil have the aſſiſtance of the Spirit of Truth, we muſt be ſure that they love God, and keep his Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; but of this we cannot have ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, their own Hiſtories relating,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:59434:38"/>and the world knowing enormous vices in them.</p>
               <p>What they alledge out of St. <hi>Paul</hi> writing to <hi>Timothy,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Tim. 3.15.</note> that <hi>the Church is the pillar and ground of Truth:</hi> we freely admit it as due to the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal Church, not to any particular; but leſs to one found guilty of ſo many and great errours, ſuch as the <hi>Romiſh</hi> is; whoſe ambition in claim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and appropriating to it ſelf all the commendations delivered of the Church Univerſal, is no leſs repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſible, than as if the Scribes and Phariſees perſecuting our Saviour, ſhould appropriate to their Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue all the praiſes given to <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron.</hi> Would not you won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that their chief Champion Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellar de ſum P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n l.</hi> 4 <hi>c</hi> 2.</note> ſhould bring for proof of the Pope's Infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that in the Old Law God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded Two <hi>Hebrew</hi> words, <note place="margin">Exod. 20.</note> or Two ſtones, ſignifying <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> to be put in the breaſt plate of the High Prieſt? And what
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59434:38"/>then? will you infer thence more Infallibility in the Pope, than in thoſe High Prieſts you bring for ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample? Will you make them all In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, even <hi>Caiphas?</hi> If we will ſpeak in earneſt, I would ſuppoſe theſe words ſo inſerted, were an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement to the High Prieſt, that he was to exerciſe Doctrine and Truth, as becoming his place. The ſame advertiſement I allow the Pope ſhould have; and I wiſh he did always do accordingly. This is the utmoſt That Text can afford. And of this weight are the other Texts they bring, to aſſure us of the Infallibility, pretended to build all our Belief on.</p>
               <p>This main Foundation of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Church being thus weakned; I began with more liberty to pry in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, and examine exactly, the Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and Tenents of both parties, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant and <hi>Romiſh.</hi> To which pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, if I had no other notice of the Proteſtant cauſe than that afforded
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:59434:39"/>by Popiſh Writers and Informers (as long time I had not) I ſhould have been for ever kept from adhering to it. Here I perceived a great Inſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity of dealing in the proceeding of <hi>Romaniſts;</hi> who to make odious their Adverſaries, gathered up out of the Writings of ſome particular perſons, a heap of ſome extravagant doctrines; adding thereto humane frailties of their private lives, (whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther true or falſe, I will not debate now) but certainly ſuch, as any wiſe and modeſt Proteſtant would ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor no leſs than any of themſelves; And if he were to repay them in the like coyn, he may by their own mouth do it ſuperabundantly. For Two certain Families or Orders of them, reputed the moſt learned and grave of all, (but very oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite in doctrine) paſſing from the Gravity of Scholaſtick Diſputes to the Scurrility of Infamatory Libels, have publiſhed of late ſuch damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble doctrines, and hideous vices,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59434:39"/>the one of the other, as any humane, and more a Chriſtian heart, would tremble to hear. Which, leſt I ſhould defile this ſacred place, or your ears, or my own mouth, I will not relate now. But I thought it fit to inſinuate to them, that this foul and killing Armour of their own againſt themſelves is in a readi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, if our neceſſary defence would require to draw it; but ſuch a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity not intervening, I think it unbecoming an Evangelical Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to ſtir that dung; and indeed no effective way to conclude with ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous minds upon ſo weighty a matter; being certain, that in all Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of men there are defects in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars. The true and proper way (being to deal as becomes men of ſolid and ſerious temper) is, to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine theſe Tenents wherein each party doth generally agree with publick Uniform conſent: which I have done:</p>
               <p>And beginning with the Church
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59434:40"/>of <hi>England,</hi> I find the eminent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of it, by Uniform conſent of word and writing, <note place="margin">Article 20.</note> aſſert the ſumme of their Faith and Religion to be the Word of God, contained in the undoubted Canonical Scripture; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides which, &amp; the plain indubitable conſequence of it, they require no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to be believed as matter of Faith. What rule could be imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned more ſacred and excellent than this, for the inſtruction of men in Faith, and good manners? if you fancy Infallibility or Antiquity, what more Infallible or Ancient than the eternal Word of God? if Sanctity and W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſedom, what can be imagined more holy and wiſe, than the councels of Chriſt our Saviour, the ſentences of holy Prophets and Apoſtles? if the Luſtre of Miracles, what more admirable and certain than thoſe wrought by our Saviour, and his Prophets, and Apoſtles, in confirmation of their doctrine? if Univerſality, all true Chriſtians
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59434:40"/>do agree in embracing and honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Canonical Scripture.</p>
               <p>Now as to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church; the Tenents of it, as oppoſite to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, ſhall be conſidered for the preſent to be reducible to theſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven heads. Firſt, the Infallibility and Supremacy of the Pope. Secondly, the Myſtery of Tranſubſtantiation. Thirdly, the Worſhip of Images. Fourthly, the Praying to Saints and Angels. Fifthly, the Half Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion denied to the Laity. Sixthly, the uſe of Indulgences, and doctrine of Purgatory. Seventhly, the cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brating of publick Divine Worſhip in a Language generally unknown to the people, and prohibiting the generality the reading of the Holy Scriptures.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Pope's Infallibility.</head>
               <p>As to the Firſt, we have already declared how ill grounded their
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59434:41"/>pretence to Infallibility is. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>St. Tho.</hi> 22. <hi>q.</hi> 13. <hi>Art.</hi> 3. <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>iman. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 4. <hi>tr</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>0. <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> Now it remaineth to ſhew how heinous a crime it is to attribute it to the Pope or his Council. Their own Divines with St. <hi>Thomas Aquinas</hi> do agree, in aſſerting, that of all ſins Blaſphemy is the greateſt. <note place="margin">1 <hi>p q</hi> 16 <hi>ar.</hi> 18 30.</note> The ſame Divines do accord in ſaying, it is Blaſphemy to attribute to any crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture what is proper to God; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as God's Attributes are indiſtinct from himſelf, and ſo to aſcribe any of them to a creature, is to make ſuch a creature God. Now, that Infallibility is one of Gods chief Attributes, incommunicable to any creature, <note place="margin">1 <hi>p. q</hi> 16. <hi>ar.</hi> 8.</note> the ſame St. <hi>Thomas</hi> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth expreſly; grounding his Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon theſe words of the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Pſalm, <note place="margin">Pſal. 11.1.</note> according to the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> Tranſlation; <hi>Quoniam diminu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tae ſunt veritates à filiis hominum,</hi> that verities are maimed among the children of men. To which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonant the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Tranſlation of the ſame Text, that <hi>the faithful
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59434:41"/>fail from among the children of men:</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Pſal. 115. v. 11.</note> but more reſolutely the hundred and fifteenth Pſalm declareth that <hi>all men are lyars.</hi> Therefore the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts</hi> Attributing Infallibility of Doctrine to their Pope, are guilty of Blaſphemy, the moſt hainous of all crimes; which is evidently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced from premiſſes of their own Theologie.</p>
               <p>This hainous Blaſphemy of paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelling the Pope with God in the At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribute of Infallibility, is raiſed to a higher degree in their practice of making him Supreme and Abſolute Judge and Arbiter of the Law of God and his Holy Scripture. So as for the belief and practice of all, we muſt ſtand to his Declaration; in ſuch degree, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min. li</hi> 4. <hi>de Rom. Pont. c.</hi> 5.</note> that <hi>Bellarmine</hi> ſtick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not to ſay, if the Pope did command Vices and prohibit Virtues, the Church would be obliged to believe Vice to be good and Virtue bad. Nay the Council of <hi>Conſtance</hi> profeſſedly commandeth the Popes
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59434:42"/>Decrees to be preferred to the Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of Chriſt. Whereas confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing that our Saviour did ordain the giving of the Sacred Communion under both kinds to the Faithful people; and that the Apoſtles and Primitive Church did practiſe it ſo: notwithſtanding they command, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Concil. Conſtan. Seſs.</hi> 13.</note> that for the future it be not given to the Laity, but under one kind. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing no other reaſon for it, than that the precedent Popes and Church govern'd by them, practiſed it ſo; though contrary to the practice of Chriſt and His Apoſtles. Whereby they extol the Pope to a degree Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periour to God himſelf in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of humane kind. If the Laws of <hi>England</hi> were not to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood or practiſed in <hi>Ireland,</hi> but according to the will and declaration of the King of <hi>France;</hi> certainly the King of <hi>France</hi> would be deemed of more Power and Authority in the Government of <hi>Ireland,</hi> and the people more Subject to him than to
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:59434:42"/>the King of <hi>England:</hi> So if the Law of God is to be meaſured by the Popes will and declaration: cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly the Pope is above God in the Government of man kind.</p>
               <p>Who would believe that any Chriſtian would preſume to ſay, that it ſhould be a greater ſin to tranſgreſs an Eccleſiaſtick Law of the Pope, than to break the Law of God?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Coſterus c.</hi> 15. <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiridii. propoſ.</hi> 9.</note> yet <hi>Coſterus</hi> one of the chief de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Doctrine, ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cketh not to ſay ſo much; reſolutely aſſerting that it is a greater ſin in a Prieſt to Marry, than to commit Fornication or keep a Concubine in his houſe: That Greater ſin, in his opinion, being but a tranſgreſſion of a Papal Law; and the other reputed by him for Lighter, a treſpaſs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Law of God expreſſed in his Divine Decalogue. What Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ears can abide to hear ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecrable Blaſphemies? will they won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der now that the Pope ſhould be taxed with that Antichriſtian Impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59434:43"/>declared by <hi>Daniel</hi> the Prophet, <note place="margin">Dan. 11.36. 2. Theſſa. 2.4.</note> and by St. <hi>Paul, who oppoſeth and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alteth himſelf above all that is called God?</hi> Here you ſee the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church guilty of that Abomination mentioned in our text<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of extolling man above God.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Pope's Supremacy.</head>
               <p>To this enormity of robbing God of his prerogatives, is joyned ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of making the Pope Supreme Head, and Maſter of all Chriſtians; not only in ſpiritual matters, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in their temporal intereſts, with power to depoſe Kings, and move their Subjects to Rebellion againſt them, when they do not obey his will; as it was declared in the <hi>Lateran</hi> Council under Innocent the Third by theſe terrible words: <hi>If a temporal Lord warned by the Church doth neglect to purge his Land of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſie, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Concil Laterar. c.</hi> 3.</note> let him be excommunicated by
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59434:43"/>the Metropolitan; and if within a year he gives no ſatisfaction, let that be ſignified to the Pope, that from thence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth he may declare his Subjects ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved from their obedience to him, and expoſe his lands to be occupied by Catholicks.</hi> And ſo was done to King <hi>John</hi> of <hi>England</hi> by the ſame Pope Innocent the Third as it is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded by <hi>Polidor Virgil;</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Polidor. lib.</hi> 15. <hi>Suar. li.</hi> 3. <hi>defenſ. c.</hi> 23.</note> to the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth by <hi>Gregory</hi> the Fourth; To <hi>Frederick</hi> the 2d. by <hi>Innocent</hi> the 4th. and to ſeveral other Chriſtian Princes, as <hi>Suarez</hi> relates; making the Practice of Popes herein an Argument of their Power for doing ſo. Which kind of arguing as I was admiring in ſo exact a Schoolman, and refle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting upon the power of prejudice, and education even over the moſt ſublime wits; an ingenious Divine of the Univerſity of <hi>Dublin</hi> reply'd fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetiouſly, it was a very concluding argument, that proceedeth <hi>ab actu ad potentiam,</hi> being he <hi>did</hi> ſo, it's
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:59434:44"/>ſign he <hi>could</hi> do it; that was good for a jeſt: But <hi>Suarez</hi> to be in earn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and give conſiſtence to his argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſubſumed, that the Church Univerſal did ſee and approve of this proceeding; and the Church being Infallible, could not approve it if not Lawful. Many other contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies would have a quick deciſion, if this diſcourſe were Legal. That all ſaw it, is allowed; but that all approved of it freely, is denyed. Force and fear made them ſuffer, what they would have reſiſted if they knew how.</p>
               <p>I remit enlarging upon the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of the Pope's pretenſions here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, to another occaſion; and their unreaſonable exclamations againſt the claim of our Princes to Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of power over their ſubjects; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they pretend no other, than ſuch as the godly Kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had in their time over the <hi>Jews,</hi> and the Chriſtian Emperors in the primitive Church over their reſpective ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects;
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59434:44"/>as it is declared in the 37. Article and 2. Canon of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Only I will reflect at preſent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the cruelty the Pope has practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of late towards the unhappy <hi>Iriſh</hi> his Followers, in purſuit of his pretended power of depoſing Kings; That being no matter of Faith, nor paſſing a probable Opinion, as <hi>Azor, Peron,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Azor to.</hi> 2 <hi>li.</hi> 11. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>q.</hi> 8. <hi>Peronus in replica ſua typis data an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> 1620.</note> and other very learned Authors of his own party do declare: If we may call proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a doctrine ſo damnable, that the great Parliament of <hi>France,</hi> (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, of 200. Votes, only 6. were Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, in the year 1604.) comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded <hi>Suarez</hi> his Book containing this doctrine, to be burned by the hands of the publick Executioner; and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the Jeſuits to have their prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers exhort the people to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary doctrine; or otherwiſe they ſhould be proceeded againſt as Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors and Diſturbers of the publick peace: Beſides, all their own Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59434:45"/>generally aſſerting, that in a probable controverſie, one may with ſafety of conſcience follow the ſide he pleaſeth: Yet the Pope prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſeverely the <hi>Iriſh</hi> to diſclaim that ſeditious doctrine, let them ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer never ſo many penalties and ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picions for it. So zealous is his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs, not of the ſalvation of ſouls, but of the conſervation of his own Grandeur; in having all power up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Earth at his will, and the Crowns of Kings to ſtand or fall at his beck! is not this to exerciſe tyranny and cruelty in the conduct of ſouls?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Tranſubſtantiation.</head>
               <p>Touching the ſecond Point pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, of Tranſubſtantiation, I ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied before how prodigious that en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gagement was, and what weak Foundation they had for it in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. Now I will declare how di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly contrary to Scripture it is,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:59434:45"/>and to the doctrine of the Fathers of the Primitive Church. The Council of <hi>Trent</hi> accurſeth ſuch as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm <hi>Bread and Wine to remain in this Sacrament after Conſecration.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Trident. Seſſ.</hi> 13. <hi>can.</hi> 2.</note> And yet St. <hi>Paul</hi> teacheth us expreſly, and repeateth the ſame doctrine ſome five times over; that after Conſecration it is Bread which is broken and eaten. <note place="margin">1 Cor. 11.23, 24.</note> 
                  <hi>The Lord Jeſus the ſame night in which he was betray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, took Bread, and when he had given thanks, he brake it, and ſaid, Take, eat, this is my Body, which is broken for you; this do, in remembrance of me.</hi> Of the Bread he took in his hand, all that followeth is affirmed, to wit, that he brake it, and that it was his Body. And whereas in a literal ſenſe it could not be ſaid with truth or propriety, that the Bread was his Body, as you may not ſay with ſenſe, that a ſtick is a ſtone, he declareth immediately, that he ſpoke in a figurative ſenſe, willing it to be a commemoration
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:59434:46"/>or remembrance of him; the Bread ſtill remaining in the nature of Bread, though elevated by Chriſt's Inſtitution to a ſupernatural and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual power of giving grace to well diſpoſed Receivers. And ſo S. <hi>Paul</hi> in ſeveral verſes after, making men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Conſecrated Element, calls it ſtill Bread; <hi>as often as you eat this Bread; Whoſoever ſhall eat this Bread, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In all which St. <hi>Paul</hi> doth but conform himſelf to the words of our Saviour, which he relateth exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctly, as ſet down by St. <hi>Luke</hi> in the 22th chapter of his Goſpel, v. 19. <hi>And he took Bread, and gave thanks, and brake it, and gave unto them, ſaying, This is my Body, which is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for you: this do in remembrance of me.</hi> And when our Saviour him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf thus declareth his words to be in a figurative ſenſe, after an uſual and plain manner of ſpeaking; it is a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>order to run to a violent explicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of them, containing wonders ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſing
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:59434:46"/>humane underſtanding, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any probable ground in the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Text; as the Papiſts do to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their doctrine, with this or the like gloſs: <hi>This is my Body,</hi> that is, the thing contained under thoſe Forms, is, by converſion and ſubſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial tranſmutation, my Body. So as pretending to ſtick to the letter, they only keep the ſound of the words; and to give them ſenſe for their purpoſe, they unaware pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce a trope, or ſomething darker, a paradox, repugnant to all humane reaſoning, and nothing coherent with the context.</p>
               <p>We agree all in calling the holy Euchariſt a Sacrament; why ſhould we not then agree in taking the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions touching it in a Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal way? A Sacrament, in common, is a ſign of a ſacred thing: <hi>Signum rei ſacrae,</hi> as Divines do ordinarily define it. Why may not the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Chriſt's Body be called a ſign of his Body: Why may not
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:59434:47"/>we underſtand that to be the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt's words, when taking the Bread, he ſaid, <hi>This is my Body?</hi> to wit, this is the ſign of my Body. It being uſual to call Sacramental ſigns by the name of the things ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified by them. As St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> teſtifyeth, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Sicut er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go ſecun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum quendam modum Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentum Corporis Chriſti, Corpus Chriſti eſt,</hi> Aug. <hi>to.</hi> 2 <hi>ep.</hi> 23. <hi>ad</hi> Bonifac</note> ſaying, <hi>Sacraments are ſigns, which often do take the name of thoſe things which they do ſignifie and repreſent.</hi> And to our purpoſe ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, that <hi>after a certain manner, the Sacrament of the Body of Chriſt is the Body of Chriſt.</hi> So the Lamb being a ſign of the Paſſover, is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Paſſover, <hi>Mat.</hi> 26.17. <hi>Exo.</hi> 12.11. The Rock being a ſign of Chriſt ſuffering for us, is called Chriſt;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſmus dicitur Sepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrum: ſic hoc eſt Corpus meum,</hi> Aug. <hi>con.</hi> Fauſt. <hi>li</hi> 20. <hi>c.</hi> 21</note> 
                  <hi>and the Rock was Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.4. and Baptiſm the ſign of Chriſt's Burial, is called Chriſt's Burial, which St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> applyeth to our purpoſe, ſaying, <hi>As Baptiſm is called Chriſt's Burial, ſo is the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament of the Body of Chriſt called his Body.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:59434:47"/>
               <p>Beſides <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Non e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nim Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus dubita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit dice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re, hoc eſt corpus meum, cum ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poris ſui,</hi> Aug. <hi>to.</hi> 6. <hi>cont. Adaman. cap.</hi> 12.</note> and all other <hi>Romiſh</hi> Writers do confeſs, being not able to deny it, that the words of our Saviour, touching the ſecond part of this Sacrament, to wit, the Cup, are ſigurative: <hi>This Cup is the New Teſtament of my Bloud;</hi> Where they acknowledge a Trope in the word Cup or <hi>Calice,</hi> taking it for that which is in the Cup. Why will not they likewiſe admit the former words relating to the Bread to be fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gurative?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Non ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gamus in verbo ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix tro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pum eſſe.</hi> Bellarm. <hi>de Euch. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 11.</note> ſuch preſſing reaſons mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving to it, and ſuch terrible incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences attending their conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as hereto has been, and after ſhall be further declared.</p>
               <p>Now that the moſt Reverend Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of that happier Age taught by Chriſt and his Apoſtles were of our Opinion, taking the words of our Saviour in a Figurative ſenſe, and the Euchariſtical Bread a Type, or Sign of his ſacred Body, is clearly ſeen by their Writings, ſuch as could eſcape the blots of the <hi>Roman</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purgatory.
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:59434:48"/>Vererable <hi>Denis A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reopagita</hi> was ignorant of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation; and ſo diſtinguiſhed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the ſubſtantial ſigns and Chriſt ſignified by them, ſaying: <hi>By thoſe Reverend ſigns and Symboles Chriſt is ſignified, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dionis. Areopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gita Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rar c.</hi> 2. <hi>I no &amp; Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oniſiq. cap hier.</hi> 3 <hi>Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſtiam. vocat an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>t typon Belar. li.</hi> 2. <hi>de Eu char. c.</hi> 15. <hi>n.</hi> ſed hoc.</note> and the faithful made par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes of him.</hi> He calleth the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a Type, even after Conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as <hi>Bellarmin</hi> himſelf confeſſeth. So that according to St. <hi>Denis,</hi> the Elements of <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> in this Sacrament are Types and Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boles; which is to ſay, figures and ſigns of the Body and Blood of Chriſt; though not bare ſigns, but really exhibiting Chriſt and his Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual grace to the faithful, duly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſed: which being St. <hi>Denis</hi> his expreſſion, fully agreeth with the belief of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in this particular.</p>
               <p>St. <hi>Chriſoſtom</hi> delivereth clearly the ſame Doctrine, <note place="margin">Chriſeſt epiſt. ad. ad Caeſar. co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tr. haereſ. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pollinar.</note> ſaying that <hi>before the Pread is ſanctified we name it Bread, but the Divine Grace ſanctify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:59434:48"/>it, by the means of the Prieſt, it is freed from the name of Bread; but it is eſteemed worthy to be called the Lords Body although the nature of Bread remains in it. But</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> is moſt eminent in clearing this point, where he bringeth in Chriſt thus ſpeaking to his diſciples: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> in</hi> Pſa. 98.</note> 
                  <hi>you are not to eat this Body which you ſee, or to Drink that Bloud which my crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſhall powr forth. I have com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to you a Sacrament, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpiritually underſtood ſhall quicken you.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Contra Adaman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tium. cap</hi> 12.</note> And again he ſaith <hi>that Chriſt brought them to a banket in which he commended to his Diſciples the figure of his Body and lood. For he did not doubt to ſay This is my Body, <note place="margin">Contra <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>auſtum Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaeum.</note> when he gave the ſign of his Body.</hi> And in another place he ſaith; <hi>that which by all men is called a Sacrifice is the ſign of the true Sacrafice, in which the fleſh of Chriſt after his aſſumption is celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Sacrament of remembrance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theodoret</hi> is more emphatical upon this ſubject, ſaying; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reus Dia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>log</hi> 2 <hi>c.</hi> 24.</note> 
                  <hi>Chriſt honoured
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59434:49"/>the Symboles and the Signs which are ſeen, with the title of his Body and Blood; not changing the nature, but to nature adding grace. For neither do the miſtical ſigns recede from their nature; for they abide in their proper ſubſtance, figure and form, and may be ſeen and touched</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <p>I will conclude theſe teſtimonies with one that haply may carry more weight, if not deemed Infallible, I mean of Pope <hi>Pelagius,</hi> ſpeaking thus: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pelagius Papa de duabus naturis contra Euri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chem &amp; Neſtori um. vide Picherel in diſſert de miſſa &amp; expo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſitione verborum inſtitutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis caenae Domini. Pag.</hi> 14.</note> 
                  <hi>Truly the Sacrament of the Body and Blood of Chriſt which we receive is a Divine thing; for that by it we are made partakers of the Divine nature; and yet it ceaſes not to be the ſubſtance or nature of Bread and Wine. And truly an Image and ſimilitude of the Body and Bloud of Chriſt is celebrated in the Action of the myſteries.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I am to ſuppoſe it will be replyed (for ſome exception muſt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived againſt evidences ſo clear and executive) that theſe teſtimonies of
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:59434:49"/>the Fathers are not to be ſeen thus in their more corrected editions; which I have reaſon to believe, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſeen the venerable writings of the moſt ancient and grave Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers of the Church, both Greek and Latine, defaced with large blots, whereſoever they were found op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the preſent Tenents and practice of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the direction of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Expurgatory. They pretend that Proteſtants have inſerted into the Books of the Fathers, thoſe clauſes favouring their own Doctrine. But who can believe, that ſo many weighty Volumes making up great Libraries, ſhould be newly printed to receive thoſe ſupplies? that ſo many clear ſentences concording with the context, ſhould be ſo arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficially conveyed into the very heart and marrow of the Homilies of the Fathers? The contrary is the more credible to me, I having ſeen very ancient Libraries, which never came
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:59434:50"/>under the hands of a Proteſtant, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>purged of ſuch clauſes and ſentences according to the Rule of the <hi>Roman</hi> Expurgatory.</p>
               <p>Beſides this, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Scot. in</hi> 4. <hi>diſ</hi> 11. <hi>q.</hi> 3. <hi>Ocham ib. q.</hi> 6. <hi>Biel lect.</hi> 40 <hi>in Canon. Miſſae. R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ffens c.</hi> 1. <hi>o.</hi> 1. <hi>controv. captiv. Balil.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Scotus, Ocham, Biel, Fiſher</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rocheſter, Baſſolis, Caietan, Melchior Canus,</hi> and others, many eminent Schoolmen have affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, that the doctrine of Tranſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiation is not expreſſed in the Canon of the Bible. And certainly it was no Article of Faith, before the <hi>Lateran</hi> Council declared it for ſuch, 1200. years after Chriſt, as <hi>Scotus</hi> and others do affirm. And even after this declaration, ſeveral of their chief Teachers continued affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that Article not to be contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Scripture; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baſſolis, Cai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tan, ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>d Suar. to</hi> 3 <hi>Diſp.</hi> 46. <hi>ſec.</hi> 3. <hi>Ca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>us lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> com. l.</hi> 3. <hi>ſun.</hi> 2.</note> eſpecially <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aſſolis, Caietan, Melchior Canus;</hi> and ſo they coined it of their own heads: for they could not declare it to be revealed, if it was not in Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</p>
               <p>Their doctrine of Tranſubſtantia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Corporal Preſence of our
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:59434:50"/>Saviour in the Sacrament of the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar being thus ill grounded; conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how deſperate is their reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, in giving to the conſecrated wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer the Worſhip of Divinity; nay greater than ever they give to the true undoubted God; as is well known to ſuch as have ſeen the ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptuous pomp of <hi>Spain,</hi> and other Popiſh Countries, in adoring the Conſecrated Hoſt. Even ſtanding to their own principles, they can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be abſolutely certain of Chriſt's Corporal Preſence under thoſe Forms of Bread; That depending, as themſelves teach, from the inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Prieſt conſecrating, and his due Ordination; and this later again depending from the intention of the Biſhop that ordained him, and his legal Ordination, and ſo upward, of endleſs requiſites impoſſible to be known certainly upon any occaſion, as <hi>Bellarmine, Vega,</hi> and all their Writers commonly do confeſs.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellar. li.</hi> 3. <hi>de ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtif. c.</hi> 8.</note> What blindneſs therefore is it to give Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:59434:51"/>Worſhip to a thing they know not certainly to be more than a piece of bread?
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vega lib.</hi> 9. <hi>de ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stif. c.</hi> 17.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Some, preſſed with this Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, did anſwer that they were free from Idolatry in their practice herein, becauſe they believe that hoſt to be God. But upon this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, the <hi>Egyptians</hi> worſhipping the Sun for God, and the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Golden Calf, believing it was the true God that brought them out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> and the groſſeſt Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that ever were, may plead for excuſe from Idolatry, alledging un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wilful miſtake. To this again ſome of them reply, that they do not barely ſuppoſe Chriſt to be really preſent under the Form of bread; but that they know and believe it upon the ſame ground and motives, upon which they believe that Chriſt is God, and conſequently to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ored. Whereby certainly they give great advantage to the enemies of Chriſt's Divinity; ſeeing they make
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:59434:51"/>the truth of theſe two things equal, that is, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellar. de Chriſto, l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> the Divinity of Chriſt and Tranſubſtantiation. And of the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truth of this bold Aſſertion, I will take learned <hi>Bellarmine</hi> for judge; who when he proves the Divinity of Chriſt, goes through nine ſeveral claſſes of Arguments (of which ſix are wholly out of Scripture) with uncontrollable ſtrength and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable clearneſs. But being to prove Tranſubſtantiation out of Scripture, his only argument is from thoſe words of our Saviour, <hi>Matth.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>De Sacr. Euchar. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 19.</note> 26. <hi>Take, eat, this is my body.</hi> And finding that proof not clear enough, appeals to the Authority of Councils and Fathers, concluding the chapter thus: <hi>Though in the words of the Lord there may be ſome obſcurity, or ambiguity, that is taken away by the Councils and Fathers of the Church;</hi> and ſo paſses to that kind of proof.</p>
               <p>But whatſoever be of Scripture for Tranſubſtantiation, it is intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:59434:52"/>boldneſs to ſay, there is the ſame reaſon for the adoration of the Hoſt, as for Chriſt's Divinity it ſelf; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as for the one we have a plain com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in Scripture, and for the other nothing like it. St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells, that <hi>all the Angels are commanded to wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Son of God; <note place="margin">Heb. 1.6.</note> and that at the name of</hi> Jeſus <hi>every knee ſhall bow, of things in Heaven, <note place="margin">Phi. 2.10.</note> in Earth, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Earth.</hi> And St. <hi>John</hi> telleth from his Maſter's mouth, that the Heavenly Father commanded that <hi>all men ſhould honour the Son, even as they do the Father.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Jo. 5.23.</note> But where is the leaſt intimation given, that we are to worſhip Chriſt in the Sacramental Bread, ſuppoſing him preſent there? If you anſwer, the general command extendeth to him where ever he is preſent; I ſay you may upon that account, as well worſhip him in the Sun, and in the Moon, and in any other bread, for in all he is preſent as God.</p>
               <p>I will conclude this Point with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:59434:52"/>the argument I ſaw, taken for the moſt weighty againſt our Doctrine hitherto declared, of taking the Sacrament of the Altar for a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memoration of our Saviour, and ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual partaking of his bleſſed Body and Bloud, for the food of our ſouls to life everlaſting, without any real tranſmutation of the ſubſtances. That if the <hi>Jews</hi> did take his words in this ſenſe, they could not in reaſon ſtrive among themſelves, ſaying, <note place="margin">John 5.52.</note> 
                  <hi>How can this man give us his fleſh to eat?</hi> nor his Diſciples ſay, <hi>This is an hard ſaying, who can hear it?</hi> And Chriſt replying, did not reprehend their miſunderſtanding his words, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated his former doctrine, ſaying, <hi>Except ye eat the fleſh of the Son of man, ye have no life in you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This argument I once over-valu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but conſidering it better, I look upon it as a tacit cenſure of Chriſt's reply for non pertinent, to ſatisfie the Objection of his Hearers. Shall we pretend to underſtand their mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:59434:53"/>better than Chriſt, to whom they ſpake? or is it impoſſible that the malice of the <hi>Jews</hi> would not, or the ſimplicity of the Diſciples could notunderſtand the heighth and myſterious ſenſe of the words of our Lord? <hi>viz.</hi> that the Elements of Bread and Wine, conſecrated and taken in a Sacramental way in remembrance of his Death and Paſſion, ſhould feed to life everlaſting the Faithful, taking them with due preparation, as Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants do underſtand in conformity with the Fathers of the Primitive Church before related: but that rather they underſtood them of a corporal and fleſhy eating of his Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy as Papiſts do; and ſo repreſented Difficulties which reaſon dictated againſt the like expreſſion, ſuch as we did in the beginning of this Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcourſe. You ſay he did not correct ſuch underſtanding; but he did ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parently, replying to the Objection of his Diſciples; <note place="margin">ſo. 6.63.</note> 
                  <hi>It is the ſpirit that quickneth, the fleſh profiteth nothing:
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:59434:53"/>The words that I ſpeak unto you, they are ſpirit, and they are life.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with he draweth them from an ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of a corporal eating, to that of ſpiritual feeding, conducing to the everlaſting life of their ſouls. His reply to the <hi>Jews,</hi> ſignifies, they underſtood him, as we do of a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual eating, and miraculous operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which they would not believe: and ſo he repeateth the ſame do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine to them, with the comminati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on annexed, that if they did not eat his fleſh, they ſhould not have life in them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Worſhip of Images.</head>
               <p>As to the third point, of worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Images, it is clearly prohibited by God in the ſecond precept of the Decalogue; <note place="margin">Exod. 20.4.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt not make un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee any graven Image, thou ſhalt not bow down thy ſelf to them.</hi> This Precept they have put out of their
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:59434:54"/>Catechiſm, to give place to their own of worſhipping of Images, with the ſame honour due to the perſons repreſented by them; and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the Image of God, and Chriſt, with <hi>latria;</hi> of the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> with <hi>hyperdulia;</hi> of Saints with <hi>dulia,</hi> according to the gradua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they expreſs. This to be the general Tenent with them, <hi>Azor</hi> declareth in theſe words, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Conſtans eſt Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logorum ſententia imagines eodem <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>nore, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norari &amp; c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>li. quo colitu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. id cujus eſt image,</hi> Az<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtit mor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 1. <hi>l</hi> 9 <hi>c.</hi> 6.</note> 
                  <hi>It is the conſtant judgment of Divines, that the Image is to be honoured and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped with the ſame honour and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, wherewith that is worſhipped whereof it is an Image.</hi> Nay, they will have us believe, that God did ordain ſo much in the firſt command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſo contradicted himſelf, prohibiting in the ſecond command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, what he commanded in the firſt. <hi>Lau: Vaux</hi> in his Catechiſm to to this Queſtion; <hi>Who breaketh the firſt commandment of God, by irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of God?</hi> giveth this Anſwer; <hi>they that do not give due reverence to
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:59434:54"/>God and his Saints, or their reliques and Images?</hi> What reverence they pretend due to Images, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Deciſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne caſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientiae, p</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 2. <hi>ſect. t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>nult. Vet. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gma The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to.</hi> 5. <hi>l</hi> 15. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>ſ</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>c.</hi> 14 <hi>ſ</hi> 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Jacobus de Graffijs</hi> declares fully, according to what has been ſaid before.</p>
               <p>But <hi>Dionyſius Petavius,</hi> one of their moſt warrantable Antiquaries, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth us, that <hi>for the four firſt Centu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, and farther, there was little or no uſe of Images in the Temples or Orato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of Chriſtians;</hi> and ſuch as was, Pope <hi>Gregory</hi> declareth, it was only for Hiſtorical uſe, for information of the unlearned, not to worſhip them, and ſo writing to <hi>Serenus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Marſile,</hi> who brake down the Images that were in his Church, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gre. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſt li</hi> 7. <hi>Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſ</hi> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>9. <hi>ad Sere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num.</hi>
                  </note> ſeeing the people worſhipping them, ſaith thus; <hi>We commend you, that you have that zeal, that nothing made with hands ſhould be worſhipped; but yet we judge that you ſhould not have broken thoſe Images; for Painting is therefore uſed in Churches, that they which are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, may yet by ſight read theſe things upon the walls, which they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:59434:55"/>read in books; therefore your bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood ought both to preſerve the Images, and reſtrain the people from worſhipping them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This difference betwixt making an Image, and worſhipping of it, is confirmed by the example of the brazen Serpent, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Num.</hi> 21.9. 2 Kin. 18.4.</note> which God himſelf ordered to be made; which when onely made and looked upon, was a Medicine; but when worſhipped, it became Poiſon, and was deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>Learned <hi>Vaſques</hi> acknowledgeth, that the worſhip of God by an Image is clearly prohibited in the ſecond Commandment; and not only the worſhip of an Idol, ſaying, that <hi>it is plain in Scripture, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vaſq in</hi> 3. <hi>p. diſ</hi> 94. <hi>c.</hi> 3</note> that God did not only forbid that in the ſecond Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandment which was unlawful by the Law of Nature, as the worſhip of an Image for God, but the worſhipping of the true God by any ſimilitude.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nic. ph. l.</hi> 8. <hi>c</hi> 53</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nicephorus Calixtus</hi> relating the Hereſie of the <hi>Armenians</hi> and <hi>Jaco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bits,</hi>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:59434:55"/>ſays, they made Images of the Father, Son, and Holy Ghoſt, which he cenſures as a moſt abſurd thing? <hi>quod perquam abſurdum eſt,</hi> yet they do it in the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. But S. <hi>Clement</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> of Images in general, declareth thus: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Li.</hi> 7. <hi>Hom. &amp; in paraen.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>We have no Images in the world, it is apparently forbidden to us to exerciſe that deceit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful art: for it is written, thou ſhalt not make any ſimilitude of any thing in Heaven above, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They confeſs it is ſinful to worſhip an Image <hi>terminativè,</hi> or in it ſelf; but pretend it lawful to worſhip it <hi>relative,</hi> or for God or the Saints ſake, who is repreſented. A ſtrange way of ſerving God! to tranſgreſs his Commandment to pleaſe him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Saul</hi> was reprehended, and ſevere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly puniſhed, for this kind of offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs; when being commanded to deſtroy all that <hi>Amalek</hi> had, he ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſheep and oxen to ſacrifice to the Lord. But that fair pretext could not excuſe his diſobedience; and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:59434:56"/>what he thought religious devotion, was declared to be no better than Idolatry. <hi>Samuel</hi> intimating to him this fearful Verdict; <note place="margin">1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.22, 23.</note> 
                  <hi>Hath the Lord as great delight in burnt offerings and ſacrifices, as in obeying the voice of the Lord? behold, to obey is better than ſacrifice; and to hearken, than the fat of rams: for Rebellion is as the ſin of witchcraft, and ſtubborneſs is as iniquity and Idolatry.</hi> This be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo, when God is ſo clear and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolute in commanding not to bow down to Images, adding to this Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, (beyond others) ſpecial ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of jealouſie, and commina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ſeverity againſt infringers of it; how can bowing down to them be juſtified with colours of devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on? or excuſed from rebellion or ſtubborneſs which is cenſured to be <hi>Idolatry?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Beſides, the worſhip of an Image <hi>terminativè,</hi> and not <hi>relativè,</hi> includes a contradiction; the very eſſence of an Image including relation to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:59434:56"/>whereas nothing can be an Image of it ſelf. Wherefore the ſame precept that prohibits a termi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>native worſhip, excludes a relative. But whatſoever may be intended by theſe expreſſions, how many of the commonalty take notice of that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinction? very few certainly. When they bow down to an Image, the Image it ſelf down-right they wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip. Then generally they commit Idolatry in this practice, or at leaſt a ſin, in expoſing themſelves to a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of committing it.</p>
               <p>But what of the inconveniences of this practice? one comes to a Church or Chappel loaden with Images, and before he can recollect himſelf and think of God, his imagination and eyes run upon thoſe pictures, and he returns home more full of Figures than of Spirit.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:59434:57"/>
               <head>Inveration of Saints.</head>
               <p>Now to the Fourth; Their invo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of Saints, is contrary to God's Ordinance,
<note place="margin">Rom 8.34.</note> who hath appointed his Son Jeſus to make interceſſion for us; who is more compaſſionate, better able, and more willing than any of the Saints or Angels to help us: <note place="margin">Joh. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 16.</note> And himſelf aſſureth us, that <hi>whatſoever we ask the Heavenly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in his Name,
<note place="margin">Acts 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>2.</note> he will give it us.</hi> Contrary to this and the declaration of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> that <hi>there is not ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in any other? and that there is no other name under Heaven given among men, whereby we muſt be ſaved.</hi> The <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church teacheth her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, to call the bleſſed Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> their life and hope, <hi>vita, dulcedo, &amp; ſpes noſtra,</hi> their Redeemer and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vioreſs; <hi>Reparatrix &amp; Salvatrix de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperantis animae:</hi> their comfort and giver of ſpiritual grace, <hi>irroratrix &amp;
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:59434:57"/>largitrix ſpiritualis gratiae;</hi> with other extravagancies, certainly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>welcome to that glorious Mother of Chriſt, and true humble ſoul, who in that her famous canticle acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth her very lowlineſs to be the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive of God's high favours to her,
<note place="margin">Luke 1.46.</note> 
                  <hi>for he hath regarded the lowlineſs of his Hand-maiden.</hi> The like exorbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tancies they preach and teach of other Saints. As I was conſidering this Point, came to my hands a paper of my own, cenſuring the doctrine I heard in a Sermon preached where I was preſent, in the City of <hi>Palencia</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> the year 1661. by a Fryer of a certain Order, upon the Feſtivity of one of their Saints, ſaying of him, that he was incapable of erring in his doctrine; that his doctrine was of equal authority with the Bible; that whatſoever ſuch a Saint did ſay, (though falſe in it ſelf) he ſaying it, muſt be true. The proofs he brought for theſe deſperate poſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, were as mad as the poſitions
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:59434:58"/>themſelves, and ſo ridiculous, that dare not relate them in this grav Auditory, though I have them in writing. Let not malice gather by this diſcourſe that I revile the Saints, or repine at their glory; I rejoyce at it, and bleſs God for ſo rewarding his Servants. What I reprehend, is, the blaſphemous abuſes committed in the worſhip of them, unpleaſing certainly to the Saints.</p>
               <p>A facetious expreſſion of a <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Preacher, may be a ſerious proof of this being ſo. Preaching upon the Feſtivity of a Saint, Founder of a certain Order, he feigned, that ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dying his Sermon, he had an extaſie or dream, wherein finding himſelf in Heaven, he ſaw that Saint he preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of behind the door, hiding him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; and being queſtioned why he did ſo? anſwered, He came there, being aſhamed to hear the mad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions of his Fryer's, in praiſing and extolling him upon ſuch days.</p>
               <p>And certainly, if the Saints living
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:59434:58"/>in glory were capable of ſhame and ſorrow, they would grieve and be aſham'd at the proceedings of their wild worſhippers. Of this I made grievous complaints to the Inquiſitor General of <hi>Spain,</hi> crying againſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orbitancies of that kind, repugnant to all Chriſtianity; being commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned by himſelf to give him ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of what doctrine I found cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurable. Even then, and in that Countrey, I cried againſt theſe exor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitancies: but how ſuccesful my good intention to that purpoſe was, I do not know; for this malady groweth ſtill: The way of getting the credit of a ſound Catholick with the blind Vulgar, is, to exceed in this Practice: as to ſpight the <hi>Jews,</hi> and ſeem true Chriſtians, they will eat more Pork than their ſtomach can bear: ſo to ſpight Proteſtants, they will run beyond all meaſure, even of their own principles, in ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancing Saints: For one Church de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicated to our Saviour, you will ſee
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:59434:59"/>an hundred dedicated to divers Saints; for one <hi>Pater noſter,</hi> ten <hi>Ave Maries;</hi> for one diſcourſe or praiſe of God, a thouſand of their reſpective Saints. Whereof I often ſaw, to my deep grief, ſad experiences. A perſon of Quality lyes dying; in comes a Fryar of this Order, and falls with all his Rhetorick to exhort him to devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards the Saints of his own Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; to take the habit, ſcapulary or cord of it. Then comes one of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Order, and falls likewiſe a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending the Saints and habit of his Order, and ſo each one as they come. Among them all, little or no menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Saviour Jeſus his Paſſion to rely upon. Would you think it is the good of that ſoul, or the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Saint, they are zealous for; or rather the intereſt of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent? judge it you, and let others of more liberty ſpeak it. Have pity O good God, of ſouls left to ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:59434:59"/>
               <head>Half Communion.</head>
               <p>Touching the fifth point, of deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Chalice to the Laity; I think it an injury to our cauſe to ſeek after any farther proof of it, than their own Confeſſion; that our Saviour Jeſus did inſtitute, and the Primitive Church did practiſe the adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the bleſſed Sacrament under both kinds to the people, as it is uſed in the Church of <hi>England.</hi> But the <hi>Roman</hi> Church thought fit to do o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe. This confeſſion is their greateſt confuſion, and too too ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient confutation. It was to me a horror to ſee the boldneſs of the Council of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> confeſſing the foreſaid, and coming down with a <hi>non obſtante;</hi> That, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Concil. Conſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>n. l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſſ.</hi> 13.</note> notwithſtanding Chriſt's inſtitution, and the practice of the Primitive Church therein; the Council prohibited all Prieſts, under pain of Excommunication, to admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:59434:60"/>the Communion under both kinds to the Laity: For cauſes they do not expreſs, neither do we need to labour in ſearching after them, it being ſufficient for our purpoſe to know, that they can find or pretend cauſes to alter Chriſt's inſtitutions, and introduce others contrary to them. The onely reaſon they give for their Decree herein, is, the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Church, and ſome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceding Popes or Fathers, and yet acknowledging that Chriſt ordained the contrary. Is not this to <hi>tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs the commandment of God by your tradition?</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>: 15: 3.</note> is not this to agree with that attribute of Antichriſt; <hi>who op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth and exalteth himſelf over all that is called God.</hi> The Pope would ſeem to clear himſelf from that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, bearing for title, Servant of the Servants of God. <note place="margin">Gen: 27: 22:</note> 
                  <hi>The voice is</hi> Jacob<hi>'s voice, but the hands are the hands of</hi> Eſau. The Pope's ſpeech in calling himſelf <hi>Servant of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of God,</hi> is Chriſtian; but his
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:59434:60"/>Deed in preferring his own Law and Inſtitution, to the Inſtitution of Chriſt, is Antichriſtian.</p>
               <p>They cry Antiquity and Authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Church for this practice; and in the ſame breath they diſclaim greater Antiquity, and more warran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Authority of the Church, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledging, that Chriſt did inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute, and the Primitive Church did practiſe the giving of the Sacrament under both kinds to all the people. How inconſequent is errour? This onely inſtance may aſſure us, that the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion, as it ſtands now, did not proceed intirely from Chriſt and his Apoſtles.</p>
               <p>If we object, that the detracting of the Cup, is the bereaving the faithful people of their ſpiritual food to life everlaſting, by not permitting them to partake of the bloud of Chriſt, he affirming, <note place="margin">Jo: 6.5 3.</note> that <hi>except ye eat the fleſh of the Son of man, and drink his bloud, ye have no life in you.</hi> The Council tells us, <hi>We muſt firmly
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:59434:61"/>believe, and no way doubt, that the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire body and bloud of our Saviour, is contained as well under the Form of bread, as under the Form of wine.</hi> But we have ſhewed before, how little ground we have for a firm belief of their doctrine in this point. How great reaſon to doubt it, nay, to be aſſured of the contrary; and that Chriſt is preſent and taken in the Euchariſt, onely in a ſpiritual and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cramental way: that being ſo, in be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaving the Faithful of the Cup, they bereave them of the whole Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. For their own Divines do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree in affirming, that the conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Forms of Bread and Wine are eſſential Conſtitutes of this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Suar. in</hi> 3 <hi>p: diſp:</hi> 42: <hi>ſec.</hi> 1 <hi>conc:</hi> 3:</note> any, they alone are the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment properly, as <hi>Suarez</hi> declares, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating a great number of other Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines for the ſame doctrine. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore taking no Wine, they take no Sacrament; taking no Sacrament, they have no life in them, as our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour declared; and ſo bereaving
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:59434:61"/>them of the Sacramental wine, they bereave them of the life of their ſouls; and is not this to uſe cruelty to ſouls?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Purgatory and Indul. gences.</head>
               <p>As for the ſixth Article, concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Purgatory, I do not find their Learned men ſo confident as the Vulgar, in fixing a determinate place for it in the bowels of the Earth; with thoſe frightful qualities, their Legends do ſpecifie. Being conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to conclude from ſome places of Scripture, and by conjecture, that after this Life there muſt be ſome place to expiate or purge ſouls from Venial fins, or ſatisfie for the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral penalty due to Great ones, without determining whether that place be over, or under, or in the Earth; or whether the pain be heat, or cold, or darkneſs, or tempeſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:59434:62"/>
               <p>And as the Concluſion is obſcure, ſo is the inference of it from the premiſſes laid. The chief place out of the Old Teſtament, is the caſe of <hi>Judas Macchabeus,</hi> ſend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing money to <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> that ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſhould be made for his ſouldiers defunct, and the gloſs annexed, <hi>that therefore it is a holy conſideration to pray for the dead, &amp;c.</hi> But though the Book relating thiscaſe were cano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nical, and of certain authority, (which is not allowed) yet the concluſion pretended from it, for the doctrine of Purgatory, is not of force. For, Prayers for the dead may be made, and were made, to different purpoſes,
<note place="margin">2 Mach. 12.43.</note> than that of drawing them out of Purgatory. Firſt,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Suar: to.</hi> 1. <hi>in</hi> 3. P. <hi>diſp.</hi> 10. <hi>Sec.</hi> 4.</note> becauſe many learned Writers of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> party do teach, that God, as a good Paymaſter, doth of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes give before-hand, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of ſervices to be done in the future; and therefore being long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſighted, and always preſent to all
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:59434:62"/>the ſpaces of Eternity, may ſee now and liſten to prayers, that will be made in any Age after. And fore-ſeeing, that godly perſons ſhall pray in the future, for the aſſiſtance of his Grace, to one dying now, may yield it accordingly. This doctrine I have ſeen practiſed in a Letter, written to my ſelf, by one of the learnedeſt men in <hi>Spain,</hi> wherein ſpeaking of the death of his Mother, he prayed to God that he might have aſſiſted her in the later hour for dying penitent. If this go well, Prayers may be commendable for the Dead to different purpoſes, from that of drawing them out of Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory. And if the caſe related of the <hi>Macchabees</hi> be true, it is more likely the prayers made for the ſlain ſhould have proceeded in the manner fore-ſaid, than for bringing them out of Purgatory. Whereas in the ſame place is related, that thoſe men were found to have committed a mortal ſin, (which is not pretended to be
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:59434:63"/>pardoned in Purgatory) <hi>under the coats of every one that was ſlain,
<note place="margin">2 Mac. 12 V. 40</note> they found things conſecrated to the Idols of the</hi> Jamnites, <hi>which is forbidden to the</hi> Jews <hi>by the Law.</hi> And though <hi>Bellarmine</hi> pretends the ſin of thoſe men ſhould be venial through igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, it is but a bare conjecture, and not agreeable to the context, ſhewing that deed to have drawn upon them God's vengeance: <hi>then every man ſaw that this was the cauſe wherefore they were ſlain.</hi> Their death might have been their tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral puniſhment; and final penitence might have freed them from the eternal, as <hi>Bellarmine</hi> confeſſeth, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lating for it the <hi>Pſalm</hi> 78. <note place="margin">Pſ. 78.34.</note> 
                  <hi>Cùm occi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deret eos, quaerebant eum, &amp; reverte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bantur; when he ſlew them, then they ſought him, and they returned and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired early after God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But not to rely upon the fore-mentioned conſideration of ſome particular Writers, if we find in ſome of the Ancients, prayers to be
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:59434:63"/>made for the dead, it was to other ends than to draw them out of this ſuppoſed Purgatory. Firſt, to praiſe God for giving them a happy end in his holy Faith, and reſt from their labours, as appeareth by thoſe words of the Revelations uſed by the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Church in the Office of the dead: <note place="margin">Rev 14 13.</note> 
                  <hi>Bleſſed are the dead which dye in the Lord, from henceforth, yea, ſaith the ſpirit, that they may reſt from their labours.</hi> Secondly, that we ſhould comfort each other in the death of our Friends, reflecting upon the hope of meeting them in Heavenly glory, according to thoſe comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble words of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in his firſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">1 Thſſ, 4.13.</note> accuſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to be read in the ſame Office of the dead; <hi>I would not have you to be ignorant, brethren, concerning them which areaſleep, that ye ſorrow not even as others which have no hope, &amp;c.</hi> third ly, for our ſpiritual inſtruction whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſidering the good example of our faithful Brethren preceding;
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:59434:64"/>whether reflecting upon our mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at the ſight of death.</p>
               <p>All this may be ſeen by the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the primitive Chriſtians, as it is declared by the Authour of the Commentaries upon <hi>Job,</hi> inſerted among the Works of <hi>Origen,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>li.</hi> 3 <hi>comment. in</hi> Job.</note> by theſe words: <hi>We obſerve the memorials of the Saints, and devoutly keep the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of our parents or friends which dye in the Faith, as well rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing for their refreſhing, as requeſting alſo for our ſelves a godly conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Faith. Thus therefore do we celebrate the death, not the day of the birth, becauſe they which dye ſhall live for ever: and we celebrate it, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling together religious perſons with the Prieſts, the Faithful with the Clergy; inviting moreover the needy and the poor feeding the Orphans and Widows, that our feſtivity may be for a memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial of reſt to the ſouls departed, whoſe remembrance we celebrate, and to us may become a ſweet ſavour in ſight of the eternal God.</hi> Whereby you ſee,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:59434:64"/>prayers and deeds of charity uſed in exequies of the dead, without men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Purgatory.</p>
               <p>This ſame Anſwer may ſerve for what <hi>Bellarmine</hi> relateth out of the fourth Chapter of <hi>Tobias,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Tob. 4.</note> touching Bread and Wine to be brought to Funerals, and the cuſtom of inviting Friends, and feeding the poor. What he alledgeth of paſſing by fire, <note place="margin">Pſal. 66.12.</note> out of the 66. Pſalm, <hi>We went through fire, and through water, but thou broughteſt us out into a wealthy place;</hi> is as little effective to the purpoſe; for by fire, as well as by water, are underſtood tribulations and croſſes of this life.</p>
               <p>What they alledge out of <hi>Math.</hi> 22. where our Saviour ſaith, that ſome ſins ſhall not be pardoned, <hi>nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in this world, nor in the world to come;</hi> therefore ſome ſins are par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned after this life, is no good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence; for from a negative, follows not a poſitive: as from ſaying the Duke of <hi>Venice</hi> is not Earl of <hi>Dublin,</hi>
                  <pb n="88" facs="tcp:59434:65"/>it follows not therefore, <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>c.</hi> 4.</note> ſome other is Earl of <hi>Dublin. Bellarmine</hi> ſays, the former conſequence ought to be held for good, according to the laws of prudence, if not according to the rules of Logick; leſt Chriſt ſhould be thought to ſpeak improperly, if no ſin were to be pardoned in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther world. But upon this account you are to admit for lawful, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the rules of prudence, this o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conſequence; <note place="margin">Mat. 1.25.</note> 
                  <hi>Joſeph knew not his wife, till ſhe had brought forth her firſt-born Son;</hi> therefore he knew her after, leſt the Evangeliſt ſhould be found improper in his delivery. And as <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> or any other Chriſtian will not think himſelf obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to admit this later conſequence, ſo neither do we think it juſt to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the former.</p>
               <p>The Doctrine of Purgatory being ſo weakly grounded, the inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of it are very great, making people negligent of true repentance and ſatisfaction for their ſins in this
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:59434:65"/>life in hopes of Remiſſion in Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory. Beſides the occaſion it gives to piniful abuſes in the valuation of Maſſes for ſtipend, wherein Simony would appear if that great ſkill of Caſuiſts did not prevent it where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with any ſale of Sacred things is ſanctified and freed from Simony by ſome dreſs of intention. What of the cheats uſed in receiving ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtipends from ſeveral perſons for one Maſs? Of the cruelty uſed with widdows, children and ſometimes with creditors of the perſon dying bequeathing what is their right up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Clergy ſometimes not in any great need of it. Wherewith un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſhape of piety great impiety is often practiſed. But the vaſt lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre accruing to the Clergy from this Doctrine, (more than any text they have for it) does engage them for the maintaining of it.</p>
               <p>The Doctrine of Indulgences ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving that of Purgatory hath the ſame obſcurity in the aſſertion and uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty in the foundation of it as the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:59434:66"/>former. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Suar. lib <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> de fenſ fid. c.</hi> 15.23.</note> 
                  <hi>Suarez</hi> declareth that In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence is nothing elſe but a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of the pains of Purgatory which God of his infinite goodneſs through the Excellent merits of Chriſt (to which he addeth the ſatisfaction of Saints) hath granted to his Church together with the power of abſolving. Of the infinite goodneſs of God, and infinite merit of Chriſt, no Chriſtian may doubt, as neither of the power of abſolving given to his Church. But whether this power extendeth to the profuſe grant of Indulgences practiſed at preſent by the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, <hi>Suarez</hi> is not ſo certain of, giving onely for ground thereof Eccleſiaſtical tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ancient cuſtome generally approved.</p>
               <p>But neither is the tradition ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, nor the cuſtome ſo ancient or generally approved, as is pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. The Firſt we meet is that of <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeventh given to thoſe of his party who would fight againſt the Emperour <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:59434:66"/>which <hi>Baronius</hi> relates from his pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitentiary, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baron. ad An. D.</hi> 1084. <hi>n.</hi> 15.</note> in which was promiſed remiſſion of all their ſins to ſuch as would venture their lives in that holy war. The like Indulgence with remiſſion of all their ſins was grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to thoſe who would fight againſt the <hi>Sarazens</hi> in <hi>Affrica</hi> by Victor ſucceeding <hi>Gregory</hi> the ſeventh. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Popes following continued the ſame practice. Then private Biſhops began to publiſh Indulgences to thoſe that would give money to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the building or repairing of Churches or other publick works promiſing pardon of the ſeventh or Fourth or third part of their ſins according as their bounty deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Vide Morin. de Paenit, lib.</hi> 10. <hi>cap.</hi> 20.</note> So as <hi>Mauritius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Paris</hi> is ſaid to have built the great Church of <hi>Noſtredame</hi> there in this manner.</p>
               <p>But the Biſhops of <hi>Rome</hi> abridged other Biſhops of this power, and made great complaints <hi>that by the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſcreet uſe of Indulgences by the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, the keys of the Church were
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:59434:67"/>contemned and the diſcipline loſt,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Council. Laetera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nens. ſub Innoc.</hi> 3. <hi>can.</hi> 92.</note> ſo <hi>Innocent</hi> the third in the <hi>Lateran</hi> Council. I wiſh the preſent Popes had regard to the like inconvenien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces ſtill following their great pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſeneſs in granting indulgences cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured not onely by their adverſaries, but by the more ſober of their own party, ſeeing clearly ſordid lucre to have a great ſhare in the conduct of them, and looſe livers give reins to their vices in expectation of thoſe boundleſs pardons, whoſe exceſſes I leave for others to relate, and to be conſidered by ſuch as ſee them. <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aquin. ſupl ſum. q.</hi> 25. <hi>art.</hi> 20. <hi>Bonavent in</hi> 4. <hi>ſent. diſt.</hi> 20 <hi>q.</hi> 6.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Aquinas</hi> &amp; <hi>Bonaventure</hi> do tell that <hi>there were ſome in the Church who ſaid the invention of Indulgences was onely by a Pious fraud to draw men to charitable Acts, which otherwiſe they would not have done; as a Mother that promiſeth her child an aple to run a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, which ſhe never gives him, when ſhe hath brought him to it.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Dur. in</hi> 4. <hi>diſt.</hi> 20 <hi>q</hi> 3.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Durandus</hi> a learned and ſincere writer confeſſeth that <hi>very little can
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:59434:67"/>be affirmed with any certainty concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Indulgences becauſe neither the Scriptures ſpeak expreſly of them, and the Fathers</hi> Ambroſe, Hillary, Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine, Hierom <hi>ſpeak not at all of them.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">Major ibi.</note> John Mayor adds that <hi>though it be a negative argument yet it is of force be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in the time of thoſe Fathers they were very much ſkilled in Scriptures, and it were very ſtrange if Indulgen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces were to be found there, that they did not find them.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Bellar de amiſs. gratia li.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>reſp: ad object.</hi> 6.</note> Add to this what <hi>Bellarmin</hi> ſaith excellently that <hi>in things which depend on the will of God nothing ought to be affirmed unleſs God hath revealed it in the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture.</hi> And conclude that the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Indulgences being not found in the Holy Scripture as now declared, you ought not to build up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it the hopes of your Salvation: but endeavour with fear and trem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling to ſecure it by exact keeping of the Commandements of God, and following the Councels of Chriſt towards a perfect life and true repentance of your ſins.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:59434:68"/>
               <head>Publick Prayer in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Language.</head>
               <p>I will conclude this ſurvey of <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh</hi> Tenents with the ſeventh and laſt point propoſed of their Latin Maſs, and prohibiting their flock the reading of Holy Scripture. And as to the former, of having publick prayers in a Language generally un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known to the people, certainly the whole 14th. Chapter of St. <hi>Paul</hi> in his firſt Epiſtle to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> is clearly againſt it. For whatſoever may be cavilled touching the Object of his diſcourſe, his reaſons do evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently conclude our purpoſe, ſhewing with admirable arguments, and very appoſite examples, how improper and abſurd an undertaking it is to ſpeak to a people in a Language they un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not, pretending to teach or edifie them. The purpoſe of nature by ſpeaking is to communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:59434:68"/>the ſenſe of him that ſpeaketh to the hearer: But how can that be if the hearer perceiveth not the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the words he ſpeaketh. <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14. v. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven things without Life</hi> (ſaith the great Apoſtle) <hi>giving ſound, whither pipe or harp, except they give a diſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the ſound, how ſhall it be known what is piped or what is harped? For if the Trumpet give an uncertain ſound who ſhall prepare himſelf for the bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle? ſo likewiſe you, except ye utter by the tongue words eaſie to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, how ſhall it be known what is ſpoken? for ye ſhall ſpeak unto the air.</hi> If we were to frame our ſelves a reaſon to make out our Doctrine to the full, what other could we de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe more apt and ſuitable to our pretention than this? Is not prayer ordained to raiſe up our minds to God? that is wont to be given for the definition of it, <hi>elevatio mentis in Deum,</hi> a raiſing up of our minds to God, to praiſe him or aſk favours of him? will it not be conducent
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:59434:69"/>and neceſſary for this purpoſe to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the ſignification of the Pſalms and prayers wiſely ordered to this end? to ſay Amen to a pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er you do not underſtand, may ſeem like the ſetting of your hand to a writing without knowing what it contains. What if a <hi>Jewiſh</hi> or other impious Miniſter did ſay a prayer containing Blaſphemies againſt Chriſt or curſes of the Chriſtian people preſent? muſt they ſay Amen to all?</p>
               <p>If a <hi>Perſian</hi> or ſome other that never heard of ſuch proceedings, did come into a Church and hear a congregation ſpeak loud and ſee them make geſtures, and ſhould be told that none of them knew what the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaid; would not he juſtly think them to be mad, and that the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the Tower of <hi>Babel</hi> were there revived? St. <hi>Paul</hi> calleth ſuch a practice madneſs, laying for foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, <note place="margin">1. Cor. 14. v. 26.</note> that in the Church <hi>all things ought to be done to edification.</hi> And what edification can ſovls receiue by
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:59434:69"/>the noiſe of words they underſtand not, more than by the ring of Bells. St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> declareth how abſurd a thing it is to ſpeak in a Language the Hearer does not underſtand, <note place="margin">Aug. <hi>de doctrin. Chriſt. li.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 10.</note> in theſe terms: <hi>Quid prodeſt locutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num integritas, quam non ſequitur in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tellectus audientis? cùm loquendi nul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la ſit cauſa, ſi quod loquimur non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligunt, propter quos, ut intelligant, loquimur;</hi> What profiteth any ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of ſpeech, if not underſtood by the Hearer? no cauſe being for ſpeaking, if what we ſpeak be not underſtood by them, for whoſe ſake we ſpeak, that they may underſtand. And to our purpoſe, we may in like manner aſk, what profiteth the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable providence and good Order of the Church, in diſtributing the ſelect part and choice ſubſtance of Holy Scripture upon the Offices to be read in Churches throughout the year; if the people, whoſe edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation is pretended by ſuch Offices, do not underſtand the contents of them?</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:59434:70"/>
               <p>I ſhall deſire ſuch as are not reſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be blind and to ſhut their eyes againſt light, and ſtop their ears to reaſon, that they conſider what advantage the Proteſtant peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have for improving their ſouls in this particular. They have the word of God clearly and intelligibly beaten into their ears dayly in their Liturgy. The Pſalms, Prayers, Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, Goſpels, and leſſons of the old and new Teſtament, moſt exactly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtributed upon reſpective days and Feſtivities, contain ſo much of Heavenly wiſdom and piety, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone may ſuffice to make a well di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpoſed ſoul both Holy and wiſe: and very hard muſt the heart be, that with ſuch continual ſhowers of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly doctrine, will not be mollified to piety and the fear of God. When the poor ſimple flock following the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Prieſt, wanteth all theſe pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful helps of piety &amp; vertue; Their whole exerciſe of Religion (ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the vulgar which is the far
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:59434:70"/>greater part) being to hear a Maſs now and then, and not underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a word of it (and very ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom hearing any declaration of it) do return home as wiſe as they went. I ſaw often ſome of their pious people extol the happineſs of ſome few among them, that had knowledg of Latin to underſtand the word of God read before them, for more elevating of their minds. Why will they not reflect upon the happineſs of the children of the Proteſtant Church in this particular, as in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny others, and open their eyes to ſee their deluſion?</p>
               <p>Their leaders alledge Antiquity for the practice of Divine Service in Latin. But Antiquity goes thus. In the <hi>Eaſtern</hi> Empire, the Liturgy was in <hi>Greek,</hi> becauſe that was the mother tongue in <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> the Court and head City of that Empire. And inferiour Provinces muſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to conform in publick exerciſe both of Church and State, with the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:59434:71"/>Court Language. In the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Empire, the Liturgy was in <hi>Latin,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was the mother Tongue in <hi>Rome,</hi> that was Court and Head of this <hi>Weſtern</hi> part. And <hi>Rome,</hi> under Popes pretending no leſs command in the Provinces of <hi>Europe,</hi> than it had under Emperours, muſt force all to conformity of Language with it ſelf in the publick worſhip of God; and will exact more obedience in that point than the Emperours did: For it was not for any priviledge or ſanctity conceived in the <hi>Greek</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Tongue, that Liturgies were ordered in them; but becauſe they were the Languages more generally underſtood in both Empires. And therefore exceptions from that rule, were granted to Provinces that could not conveniently obſerve it. So Pope <hi>John</hi> the eighth allowed to the Prince of <hi>Moravia,</hi> to have their Liturgy in the <hi>Sclavonian</hi> Tongue, becauſe St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith: <hi>Let every Tongue praiſe the Lord,</hi> which was the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:59434:71"/>reaſon given by the Pope in his Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, related by <hi>Baronius.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baron. to.</hi> 10. <hi>Anno</hi> 880 <hi>n.</hi> 16. <hi>Strabo de re ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſ. c.</hi> 7.</note> And <hi>Wale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fridus Strabo</hi> tells, that in his time the Divine Office was performed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Scythians</hi> in the <hi>German</hi> Tongue,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Origen cont. Ceſſ. li.</hi> 8. <hi>p.</hi> 402.</note> which was common to them and the <hi>Germans.</hi> Nay, <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> affirmeth, that in the primitive Churches, all publick Offices of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion were performed in the proper Language of every Countrey.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Scripture prohibited.</head>
               <p>And leſt they ſhould learn in their Houſes, what they cannot in their Churches, they are prohibited to read Scripture in their own Tongues, without licence under the hand of the Biſhop or Inquiſitor, by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of the Prieſt or Confeſſor, tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the perſon's fitneſs for it; and who preſumes to do otherwiſe, is to be denied abſolution. This is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded in the Fourth Rule of the
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:59434:72"/>
                  <hi>Index,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Index li. prohib. Alex</hi> 7. <hi>Rom. An.</hi> 665.</note> publiſhed by Order of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> and ſet forth by the Authority of <hi>Pius</hi> the Fourth, and ſince by <hi>Clement</hi> the Eighth, and lately enlarged by <hi>Alexander</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth. <note place="margin">Mat. 4.4.</note> This is cruelty to ſouls; Chriſt declaring the Word of God to be their food. And Scripture it ſelf ſo often inviting us to the read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of it: St. <hi>Peter</hi> thus exhorteth to it, <note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.19:</note> 
                  <hi>We have alſo a more ſure Word of prophecy, whereunto ye do well, that ye take heed, as to a light that ſhineth in a dark place till the day dawn.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> commendeth to us the reading of Scripture, as written <hi>for our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction and comfort,
<note place="margin">Ro. 15 4. 2 Tim. 3.15. Act. 17.11.</note> and as able to make us wiſe unto ſalvation.</hi> St. <hi>Luke</hi> praiſeth the Inhabitants of <hi>Berea, in that they received the Word with all readineſs of mind, and ſearched the Scriptures daily.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Holy Fathers of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Church, were of the ſame ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of exhorting the Faithful, to the reading of Scripture for their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:59434:72"/>and direction. St. <hi>Clement,</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Clement. Epiſt. ad Corin. p:</hi> 58.</note> for remedying a diſſention happened among the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> writes thus to them: <note place="margin">
                     <hi>p:</hi> 61.</note> 
                  <hi>Look diligently unto the Scriptures, which are the true Oracles of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> He addeth after, <hi>Take St.</hi> Paul<hi>'s Epiſtles into your hands, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>p.</hi> 68.</note> and conſider what he ſaith,</hi> and prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes them for being ſkilled in the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures; <hi>Beloved,</hi> ſays he, <hi>ye have known, and very well known, the Holy Scriptures; and ye have throughly look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into the Oracles of God; <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ignatius epiſt. ad Philad. Policar. Epiſt. ad Philip. Clem. Alexand. Strom.</hi> 7. <hi>p</hi> 72.</note> therefore call them to mind.</hi> Of the ſame mind was <hi>Policarp, Ignatius,</hi> and the other Ancient Fathers. <hi>Clemens</hi> of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria</hi> mentioneth the <hi>reading of Scriptures among Chriſtians before their Meals, and Pſalms, and Hymns at them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>What makes the preſent Church of <hi>Rome</hi> ſo vigilant to the contrary, in keeping their Flock from reading Scripture? One reaſon they give, and another they keep to themſelves: the reaſon they give, is, that Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:59434:73"/>did ariſe from the abuſe of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures. Be it ſo, but who were the abuſers? certainly Prieſts, Monks, and Fryars more frequently; and of them the moſt Learned. Turn to Records, and you ſhall find it to be ſo. Then if this Argument proves any thing, it will obtain the baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Scripture from among the Learned, and out of all the world. Proving ſo much, (which is too much) it proveth nothing. Meat and drink is the ruine of many, ſhall they be ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed therefore out of the World? No, let the creatures of God ſerve his ſervants, and let the abuſers of them have their puniſhment in the very abuſe they commit. Let this Heavenly Lanthorn, which God ſet up in his Houſe, the Holy Church, to guide us in the dark ways of this life, ſhine to all Chriſtians.</p>
               <p>And, that weak eyes may not be dazled by the brightneſs of it; let this be the general rule for all to read Scripture: Where they find it
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:59434:73"/>clear, let them embrace it devoutly, and frame their lives accordingly: where it appears obſcure, let them humbly pray the Lord, he may help them with light to underſtand it, and wait patiently upon his pleaſure for doing ſo. In the mean time, they may be aſſured, that all neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary knowledge for Faith in God; to ſerve and praiſe him is fully con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in what is clear of Scripture. So St. <hi>Augustine</hi> affirmeth;
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Aug. de Doctrin. Christ. l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note> 
                  <hi>In iis quae apertè in Scripturâ poſita ſunt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniuntur illa omnia quae continent fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem moreſque vivendi.</hi> Whereof St. <hi>Paul</hi> giveth an ample teſtimony, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.15.</note> 
                  <hi>The holy Scriptures are able to make thee wiſe unto ſalvation: through Faith which is in Chriſt Jeſus: and are profitable for doctrine, for reproof, for correction, for inſtruction in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs. That the man of God may be perfect, throughly furniſhed unto all good works.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Holy Fathers do agree with St. <hi>Paul,</hi> in this his Opinion of the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:59434:74"/>profit of Scripture, for our ſpiritua<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> inſtruction. St. <hi>Baſil</hi> commends them <hi>as the beſt remedy for all the paſſions of the mind.</hi> 
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Baſil. in Pſal</hi> 1.</note> St. <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> reflect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon that great meekneſs of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> in letting <hi>Saul</hi> go free, when he had him at his will in the Den, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends to all the memory of that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chryſoſt. Homil.</hi> 1. <hi>de Davi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de &amp; Saule.</hi>
                  </note> ſaying, <hi>It is impoſſible, that a mind converſant with this kind of Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtories, ſhould be overcome with paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi> St. <hi>Jerome</hi> ſaith, <hi>that infinite evils do ariſe from ignorance of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures. From hence moſt part of He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies have come; from hence a negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent and careleſs life, and unfruitful labours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The reaſon given by <hi>Papiſts</hi> againſt reading of Scripture being thus con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futed; would you know what reaſon it is that they have, and keep to themſelves? Very many ſay it is, for keeping the people blind-folded, that they may not ſee the Ignorance of their Miniſters, nor the Corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of their Myſteries It ſeems they
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:59434:74"/>have declared ſo much themſelves, in a Council of Biſhops met at <hi>Bono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> for reſtoring the dignity of the <hi>Roman</hi> See, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Conc. de ſtabilien. Rom. fid. p.</hi> 6, <hi>apud Stilling-fleet ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re de Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lolatria, Rom. ecc. pag.</hi> 201.</note> by Order of Pope <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> the Third: the chief advice they gave, was, that <hi>by all means, as little of the Goſpel as might be, (eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the vulgar Tongue) ſhould be read in the Cities under his juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Adding that Book to have been the cauſe of that great decay of their former luſtre, and concluding thus; <hi>And in truth if any one diligently con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider it, and compare it with what is done in our Churches, will find them very contrary to each other; and our very doctrine not onely to be different from it, but repugnant to it.</hi> Thus God was pleaſed they ſhould diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their intention, &amp; that it ſhould be publiſhed for undeceiving the miſled by them, as written by ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral grave Authors; who, I ſuppoſe, would not publiſh it, but upon ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient ground. And is not this to uſe Tyranny over ſouls?</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:59434:75"/>
               <head>Third Point.</head>
               <p>Now I will come to the third and laſt Point propoſed of my Diſcourſe, which is, to conclude from what is ſaid hitherto, that the reſolution I took of withdrawing from the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, was juſt and neceſſary. My whole Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe upon the Text prefixed, is but one Syllogiſm, whereof the <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor</hi> Propoſition is this; That if we ſhould find a Church or Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on convinced of Idolatry, Impiety, and Cruelty, in the publick eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed practice of it; we are to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake the Communion of it. This is the doctrine of our Saviour, contain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the words of our Text, as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared by the declaration and proof of it in the firſt Point. The <hi>minor</hi> is, That I found the preſent general practice of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced of Idolatry, Impiety, and Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elty: The Concluſion is, that the Reſolution I took of forſaking it, was juſt and neceſſary. No Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:59434:75"/>may deny the <hi>major,</hi> it being Chriſt's doctrine, as appeareth by our Text. If the <hi>minor</hi> be true, no good Logician may deny the conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. The truth of the <hi>minor,</hi> touching Idolatry, ſeems to be ſufficiently proved by what is ſaid concerning the Worſhip of of the Euchariſtical bread, and of Images. And touching Antichri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Impiety by what is declared of their oppoſing, and preferring the Popes Laws to the Law of God; making the Pope Sole and Supreme Arbiter of Gods Law, giving him the Attribute of Infallibility proper to God alone; abrogating Chriſts Inſtitution in the Adminiſtration of the Euchariſt or Communion, and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhing another contrary to it. Bereaving Chriſt of the title of ſole Saviour and hope of human kind, by calling the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> their Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oureſs and hope. Advancing the honour and worſhip of Saints be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond that of God, by dedicating
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:59434:76"/>more Churches, and ſaying more prayers to them than to God</p>
               <p>Their Cruelty in the conduct of ſouls appeareth too much in what we have ſaid of bereaving the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an people of the Fruit of the bleſſed Sacrament of the Altar, in their pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of half Communion: in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priving them of the benefit of their ſoul, having publick Divineſervice in a Language not intelligible to them, &amp; of the liberty of reading the word of God in his Holy Scriptures. Their Tyranny over Princes, in depoſing them from their Crowns and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and moving ſubjects to bear arms againſt them. Their ſeverity uſed with the <hi>Iriſh</hi> in purſuance of their pretention herein.</p>
               <p>To this may be added their Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny over conſciences in forcing them to the belief and defence of Doctrines repugnant to their judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and not eſtabliſhed by Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Faith; as may appear in their violence about forcing all to believe
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:59434:76"/>and declare for the conception of the virgin Mary without original ſin; ſo many clear teſtimonies of Scripture being againſt it as affirm, that all men did ſin in <hi>Adam;</hi> that Chriſt was univerſal redeemer from ſin, and Saviour of all mankind. And not one word to be found in favour of the Exception they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> beſides their voluntary, and very often fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous applications of Texts, never intended by the Author of them for their purpoſe. So whatſoever is ſaid by <hi>Solomon</hi> of the Spouſe in his Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles, of wiſedom in his <hi>Proverbs, &amp;c.</hi> that may ſeem to have ſome ſound or cadency, ſuiting with their intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is taken up for a ſure Oracle, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring the immaculate conception of the bleſſed Virgin. But what ſtrength is wanting to their Texts, is ſupplied by Force and Art; two Orders being engaged in that quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, for the immaculate conception; the one numerous among the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:59434:77"/>and violent in ſtirring them to abuſe the Houſes and perſons of their Oppoſers: the other prevalent with the Peers and Prelates, and with the Popes, to engage all in their Quarrel; obtaining fearful Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communications againſt Oppoſers of their doctrine by word or writing; ordering that in Univerſities none may have Degrees, in Churches none may preach, but ſuch as will proteſt publickly for the immaculate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception, with other many violences uſed to extort ſuch proteſtations. Of which Proteſtants how many do Proteſt againſt, what in their mind they judge to be truth, God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth. For my part, I am ſlow in judging of mens thoughts; but I dare judge, that if their Definitions tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching other Points controverted did proceed after this manner, I am not obliged to take them for Infallible.</p>
               <p>What of their cruel cenſures of their Fellow Chriſtians, not ſubject to the Pope of <hi>Rome,</hi> excluding
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:59434:77"/>them, and the reſt of human kind, not living in that Communion, from all hopes of Salvation; wherein they not onely oppoſe Truth, but bely their own Principles, as was clearly made out, in a Treatiſe I was forced to pen ſome years ago: When being queſtioned by ſome of the Nobility, whether one baptized, knowing the Lords Prayer, the Ten Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and the Creed, and endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to live according to them, ready to believe what he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtands to be true Catholick Faith, guilty of no obſtinacy in misbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving any Article of it: Whether ſuch an one may be ſaved, though he be not of the Communion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. I anſwered, he may; and was truly a Member of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, notwithſtanding any calling the Vulgar gave him. And having underſtood I was cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for this Doctrine in abſence; (though none oppoſed me in pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence) I penned a Treatiſe in <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine,</hi>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:59434:78"/>wherein I demonſtrated by evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Teſtimonies of Scripture, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cils, Fathers, Authority of Divines, and Declarations of Popes, that the Doctrine I delivered was Catholick Faith, and the contrary of it was Hereſie and Blaſphemy. Coppies of this Treatiſe were given to them of more Authority and Learning, of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Clergy in the Kingdom, and are among them theſe 3. or 4. years, and none yet could ſhew in it any thing untrue, or ill grounded; yet all conſpired againſt the publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of this ſaid Doctrine, as being prejudicial to the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Cauſe; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thence followed, that Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants may be ſaved, and that many called Hereticks, would not be ſuch indeed. To which I anſwered, that I found great conveniences in thoſe things they repreſented to me for inconveniences; being heartily de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous that all men ſhould be ſaved, and that of them called Hereticks, none of all ſhould be ſuch in truth.
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:59434:78"/>And come what will of my Anſwer, I cannot but anſwer truth when I am queſtioned.</p>
               <p>I replied to their complaints of that, with the words of <hi>Job, <note place="margin">Jo. 13.7.</note> Will you ſpeak wickedly for God, and talk de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfully for him?</hi> Or as the <hi>Latine</hi> Text hath; <hi>Num quid Deus indiget veſtro mendacio, ut pro illo loquamini dolos?</hi> Does God need your lyes, and that you ſhould uſe cheats in his cauſe? ſurely he does not. And ſo I concluded, it was not the cauſe of God, or good of ſouls, they zealed, but the Grandeur of the <hi>Roman</hi> Court, and their own pretentions with it; which I would not advance with telling lyes, or concealing truth. Let them ſooth one another with thoſe compliances, as thoſe Owls and Syrens <hi>Iſaiah</hi> repreſents, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another in the ruinous Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of <hi>Babilon; Reſpondebant ibi ulu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lae in aedibus ejus,
<note place="margin">Iſ. 13.22.</note> &amp; Syrenes in delu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bris voluptatis.</hi> Odious Night-birds, &amp; leud Syrens keep correſpondence
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:59434:79"/>in <hi>Babilon.</hi> But the children of Light, and Lovers of Truth, will not liſten to their charms, nor yield to their cheats.</p>
               <p>They deceive the ſimple with ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that Proteſtants do allow Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts may be ſaved; but Papiſts do not allow that Proteſtants may be ſaved; and thence conclude, that both parties approving of the Popiſh Religion for a ſure way to ſalvation; it is to be reputed for the moſt ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure but in neither do they ſay truth; for no learned Proteſtant does allow the Popiſh Religion in general, and abſolutely ſpeaking to be a ſecure way to Salvation. For all do agree in affirming, that many of their Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nents and practices are inconſiſtent with Salvation; though ignorance may haply excuſe many of the ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſort; but not ſuch as know, or with due care and inquiry, may know their errour.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, all learned men of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church do teach, that
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:59434:79"/>all Proteſtants baptized, <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Laiman: l.</hi> 2. <hi>tr.</hi> l. <hi>c.</hi> 13. <hi>Vaſq. q.</hi> 1. <hi>diſp.</hi> 126. <hi>Caſtropal. p.</hi> 1. <hi>tr.</hi> 4. <hi>diſp.</hi> 1. <hi>q.</hi> 11. <hi>p.</hi> 1. <hi>diffic.</hi> 4. <hi>aetatis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud ipſos.</hi>
                  </note> and belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the common principles of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Religion, not convinced of any errour againſt the Catholick Faith, but conceiving they follow the truth of it, are not Hereticks, but Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Catholick Church; and ſo endeavouring to ſerve God accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the rules of their Belief, may be ſaved, as formerly declared. And it is a high point of raſhneſs, and want of Chriſtian charity, to judge of any particular, without ſpecial ground that he does not live with that ſincerity of mind and belief, that he is in the right. Such pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous cenſures are injurious to the goodneſs of God, and Diſturbers of human quiet. For truly, if by reaſon of the diverſity of tempers, abilities, educations, and unavoidable prejudices, whereby mens underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings are variouſly formed and faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, they embrace ſeveral opinions, whereof ſome muſt be erroneous; to ſay that God will damn them for ſuch
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:59434:80"/>errours, they being lovers of Truth, and deſirous to ſerve him; is to rob man of his comfort, and God of his goodneſs. In which raſh proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the commonalty of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> party are beyond all men preſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and malignant; and their learned men that do favour, and not rebuke their malignity therein, may juſtly fear God's diſpleaſure, &amp; that Chriſt will diſown them for followers of him, as void of charity, the chief mark he gives of his Diſciples, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; <hi>by this ſhall all men know, that ye are my Diſciples,
<note place="margin">Jo. 13.3.</note> if ye have love one to another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Hereunto I may add the great ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny and cruelty they uſe to ſouls in the practice of Confeſſion. On the one ſide, they encreaſe the rigour of it with additions of ſeverity, obliging to ſuch minute expreſſions of the moſt loathſom circumſtances of ſecret thoughts and deeds, as render it the moſt heavy of Chriſtian Duties. And on the other ſide, they put ſo many
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:59434:80"/>ſtops to the execution of it, by reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of caſes not to be abſolved, but by determinate perſons; that it occaſions lamentable perplexities of ſouls, and proceedings againſt the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctates of their Conſcience. Which cruelty is farther encreaſed in many places, by the ſordid avarice of their Paſtors, making poor ſouls believe they may not confeſs but to their own Curats, and refuſing to hear their Confeſſions, without receiving Money for it. I will not be ſo unjuſt to the <hi>Roman</hi> Church, as to faſten this later abuſe upon the whole body of it, it being but the fault of ſome corrupt members. I am not ſo malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant towards her, as to throw the dirt of her feet in her face; whereas I would, if I could, waſh away all her ſtains with the bloud of my heart. But even her feet are ſo haughty, and ill ſufferers of correction, that endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to reform this abuſe, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timating Decrees of Councils and Popes againſt it, and repreſenting the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:59434:81"/>miſcarriage of ſouls by it; I had no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther fruit of my labour, but ſpight &amp; hatred, for pretending to cure this malady; which joyned to many other experiences of their diſtemper, to be both incurable and contagious, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved upon this concluſion:
<note place="margin">Jerem 51.9.</note> 
                  <hi>We would have healed</hi> Babilon, <hi>but ſhe is not hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, for ſake her.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But thou, O Father of mercy, Lord Omnipotent, to whoſe power all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures are ſubject, who canſt hold in with bit and bridle, ſuch as will not approach to thee; forſake not that Church, nor any other Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of men redeemed by the precious bloud of thy Son Jeſus. Illuminate them all with the glorious beams of thy Heavenly Light: Reduce them by the powerful tyes of thy grace, to perfect Union in Truth and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to ſerve and praiſe thee duly in this life, and joyn together in thy Glory, in Life everlaſting. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:59434:81"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
